<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-04T11:36:21+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Mihály Koltai</title><subtitle>[&quot;personal website&quot;]</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Notes, thoughts, graphs on the COVID19 pandemic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/covid-modeling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes, thoughts, graphs on the COVID19 pandemic" /><published>2020-04-18T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-04-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/covid-modeling</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/covid-modeling/">&lt;p&gt;These are some notes on the COVID19 pandemic.
They include data visualization on the pandemic, comparing its evolution in different world regions, as well as exploring some general properties of compartmental dynamic transmission (SIR-type) models.&lt;br /&gt;
The models below make no specific predictions, instead I am only looking at their general mathematical properties.&lt;br /&gt;
Finally, I have been making notes of scientific papers and preprints that caught my attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;Table of contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1-own-stuff&quot;&gt;Own stuff&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#data-visualization&quot;&gt;Data visualization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#sir-models&quot;&gt;SIR models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2-notes-on-the-literature&quot;&gt;Notes on the literature&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#dynamical-models&quot;&gt;Dynamical models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#data-and-reports&quot;&gt;Data and reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tools&quot;&gt;Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-own-stuff&quot;&gt;&lt;ins&gt;1. Own stuff&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-visualization&quot;&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Data visualization&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plots below the x-axis shows the number of cumulative reported COVID19 cases and fatalities relative to a country’s population (cases/deaths per million inhabitants).&lt;br /&gt;
The y-axis shows the 3-day average of the number of new cases or fatalities per one million inhabitants.
Time is implicit on these graphs, moving from left to right, and each data point is one day.&lt;br /&gt;
This way one can see how much of the population is known to have contracted the virus and what is the current rate of growth per one million people. This makes the situation in different countries visually comparable.&lt;br /&gt;
All data downloaded from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/CSSEGISandData/COVID-19/tree/master/csse_covid_19_data/csse_covid_19_time_series&quot;&gt;Johns Hopkins University database&lt;/a&gt; and the graphs were made in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/mbkoltai.github.io/blob/master/images/covid/covid_data.ipynb&quot;&gt;Jupyter notebook&lt;/a&gt;.
For higher resolution see the &lt;ins&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/mbkoltai.github.io/blob/master/images/covid/multiplot_growth_rate_deaths_popul_cutoff100_loglog.pdf&quot;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/ins&gt; &lt;ins&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/mbkoltai.github.io/blob/master/images/covid/multiplot_growth_rate_cases_popul_cutoff100_loglog.pdf&quot;&gt;files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
I also regularly update &lt;ins&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/mbkoltai.github.io/blob/master/images/covid/merged_cases_daily_incr.pdf&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/ins&gt; &lt;ins&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/mbkoltai.github.io/blob/master/images/covid/merged_deaths_daily_incr.pdf&quot;&gt;plots&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/ins&gt; where the daily increase in cases and fatalities are separately shown for each country in the same six world regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Dynamics of the number of reported cases&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/covid/multiplot_growth_rate_cases_popul_cutoff100_loglog.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Dynamics of the number of reported fatalities&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/covid/multiplot_growth_rate_deaths_popul_cutoff100_loglog.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also interesting to plot the time evolution of the (population normalized) number of fatalities and cases against each other and visualize the distance of the trajectory from the estimated case fatality ratio (I use 1%).
This suggests the scale of underestimation of case numbers, although the relationship is not straightforward as the demographics of infections, timing and quality of health care also affect the CFR; I track this &lt;ins&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/mbkoltai.github.io/blob/master/images/covid/merged_cases_deaths.pdf&quot;&gt;on these plots&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;.
With more testing the CFR could be converging the (forming) consensus estimate, I am plotting this process &lt;ins&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/mbkoltai.github.io/blob/master/images/covid/merged_tests_cfr.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;.
Looking at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/mbkoltai.github.io/blob/master/images/covid/cases_deaths_permillion_last_date.pdf&quot;&gt;cases/million-deaths/million scatterplot&lt;/a&gt; of countries at the most recent date we can see what countries seem to be outliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sir-models&quot;&gt;&lt;ins&gt;SIR models&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us start with the simplest epidemic model, ie. the SIR compartmental model, where we have:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{dS(t)}{dt}{=}{-}\alpha S(t) I(t) \\
\frac{dI(t)}{dt}{=}\alpha S(t) I(t)-\beta I(t) \\
\frac{dR(t)}{dt}{=}\beta I(t)
\tag{1}\label{SIR_odes}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is more convenient to work with fractions of a population (and not absolute numbers), so that we have the conservation &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S(t){+}I(t){+}R(t){=}1&lt;/script&gt;.
We need to keep in mind that this is a mean field ODE model and &lt;strong&gt;has many limitations&lt;/strong&gt;. It assumes complete homogeneity of transmission events, ie. that they depend only on the &lt;em&gt;fraction&lt;/em&gt; of the population susceptible and infected and that for given values of these fractions we have the same rate of transmissions.
This also means that any small nonzero values for the infected population will lead to transmissions, whereas in reality a very small fraction can mean so few infected individuals that the epidemic can just die out. Also, in reality transmission events (very probably) do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; occur homogeneously, proportionally to the infected (and susceptible) fraction of the entire population, but are much more clustered, local and occurring in certain environments, in burst-like (‘superspreader’) events.
For these reasons it is important to stress that these SIR models should be interpreted very cautiously and we must keep in mind their assumptions that are not entirely correct.
Nevertheless, they can give us a first idea of some general properties of epidemic dynamics and that’s what I want to do here. For predictions and planning more advanced models that take into account local environments, stochasticity, rare spreading events etc should be used, and it can also be useful to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5b68a4e4a2772c2a206180a1/t/5e8e5ac9e696ba4b972093fa/1586387658680/Modeling2.pdf&quot;&gt;very simple but probabilistic models&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the SIR framework it is clear that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I(\infty){=}0&lt;/script&gt;, since this variable has first-order (linear) decay, so any nonzero value in this compartment eventually ‘leaks out’ into &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R&lt;/script&gt;.
Therefore the equilibrium of the system is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(\overline{S},0,\overline{R})&lt;/script&gt; and due to the conservation &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{R}{=}1{-}\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt;. So to characterize the stationary behavior of the system all we need to calculate is
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course this can be done by numerically integrating the ODEs in \ref{SIR_odes} and indeed half the internet is full of SIR-models now. But how about an &lt;a href=&quot;http://http://mbkoltai.github.io/exastolog/&quot;&gt;exact solution&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;br /&gt;
In this very clear &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-020-0883-7&quot;&gt;paper in Nature Medicine&lt;/a&gt; (and probably others before) the authors explicitly derive the stationary solution for a more complicated model of 8 variables they abbreviate as the ‘SIDARTHE’ model.
Despite the apparent complexity this model is basically identical to the simple SIR model. The only difference is that 1) the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I&lt;/script&gt; variable is split into several sub-variables (&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;: infected, a-/presymptomatic, undetected, &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;: diagnosed (asymptomatic infected, detected); &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: ailing (symptomatic infected, undetected); &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;: recognized (symptomatic infected, detected); &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;: threatened (infected with life-threatening symptoms, detected)) 2) the sink variable &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; of the SIR model is split into two sinks (&lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;: healed (recovered); &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;: extinct (dead)). However the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;IDART&lt;/script&gt; ‘module’ (the five state variables representing different stages of infection) has the same basic property as &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;, namely that in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t{\rightarrow}\infty&lt;/script&gt; they decay to 0, and only &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt; can have nonzero values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the simple SIR model defined of \ref{SIR_odes} the solution for the stationary value of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt; is less complicated than in the latter model, ie. it is given by the implicit expression:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\alpha}{\beta} \overline{S} - log\overline{S} = \frac{\alpha}{\beta} - logS(0)
\tag{2}\label{SIR_S_stationary}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be solved by an efficient algebraic solver such as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;fsolve&lt;/script&gt; in MATLAB.
Let us do a parameter sweep in the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\alpha}{\beta}&lt;/script&gt; ratio and the initial value of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S(0)&lt;/script&gt;, and look at the stationary solution of &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;, ie. the fraction of the population that went through infection (ie. is now immune, if there is long-term immunity). Let us also check if the algebraic formula is the same as integrating the ODEs of \ref{SIR_odes} for a long time span:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/covid/SIR_immune_pop_algebr_ode_sol.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 1: Stationary solutions of SIR model calculated by simulations (left) and exact calculations (right)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately the analytical solutions from \ref{SIR_S_stationary} are identical with the numerical solutions of the ODEs, so we didn’t make a mistake in \ref{SIR_S_stationary}.&lt;br /&gt;
What do we see from this plot? The &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\alpha}{\beta}&lt;/script&gt; ratio is the famous &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0&lt;/script&gt;, the basic reproduction parameter, and logically, the larger this ratio is, the more of the population will go through infection (again, in the framework of this extremely simplified model not meant to be realistic).
It is also intuitive that if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S(t{=}0)&lt;/script&gt; is smaller because of a larger initial infected population &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I(0)&lt;/script&gt;, then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{H}{+}\overline{E}&lt;/script&gt; will be larger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let us make the model one step more refined, and split &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; into two variables, &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;(ealed) and &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;(xtinct , ie. deceased), as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/covid/SIHE_cropped_resiz.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 2: ‘SIHE’ version of the SIR model where &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;(recovered) is split into &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;(nfected) variable now has two outcomes. It is clear intuitively that this will not change how the stationary solution of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt; is calculated, as the sink nodes do not interact with &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;, except that now &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; has two outgoing flows, so it is the ratio &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\alpha}{\lambda{+}\tau}&lt;/script&gt; that will define &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt; as:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\alpha}{\lambda{+}\tau} \overline{S} - log\overline{S} = \frac{\alpha}{\lambda{+}\tau} - logS(0)
\tag{3}\label{SIHE_statsol_S}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover we can give the formulas for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{H}, \overline{E}&lt;/script&gt; as a function of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt; and the initial infected population &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I(0)&lt;/script&gt;.
It is reasonable to assume &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H(0), E(0)&lt;/script&gt; are 0.
Downstream of &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; the dynamics is completely linear: what flows out from &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; into &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; (ie. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta{S}{=}S(0){-}\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt;), as well as the initial concentration of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I(0)&lt;/script&gt; will be partitioned into the sink variables proportionally to the rate constants &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau&lt;/script&gt;. Specifically, we’ll have:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{H} = [(S(0)-\overline{S}) + I(0)] \frac{\lambda}{\lambda{+}\tau}\\
\overline{E} = [(S(0)-\overline{S}) + I(0)] \frac{\tau}{\lambda{+}\tau}  
\tag{4}\label{SIHE_statsol_H_E}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ratio &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\tau}{\lambda{+}\tau}&lt;/script&gt; is the infection fatality (IFR) rate.
It is clear from \ref{SIHE_statsol_S} that the IFR does not affect &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt; if the sum &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda{+}\tau&lt;/script&gt; is kept constant, it is instead the ratio of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; (rate constant of new infections) to these two parameters that determine at what level of total infections the epidemic stops.
To check if the formulas are correct, let us again compare the exact solution to the numerical solution of the ODEs, and plot the stationary solutions of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S},&lt;/script&gt; at different IFR values:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/covid/SIHE_algebr_ode_IFRscan.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 3: stationary solutions of SIHE model at S(0)=0.99 and four different values of the IFR&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Circles show the results from numerical integration of the ODEs, confirming they are identical with the analytical solutions (lines). The fraction of the population that has not been infected throughout the epidemic (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt;) goes down with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\alpha}{\lambda{+}\tau}&lt;/script&gt;, but is independent of the IFR as the sum &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;{\lambda{+}\tau}&lt;/script&gt; was kept constant here. The ratio &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\alpha}{\lambda{+}\tau}&lt;/script&gt; expresses how fast subjects exit the infectious state relative to the rate constant of generating new infections. A higher ratio means more of the population is infected, which is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{H}+\overline{E}=(S(0){-}\overline{S}){+}I(0)&lt;/script&gt;.
In contrast, if both &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda{+}\tau&lt;/script&gt; are equally scaled then this quantity does not change.&lt;br /&gt;
How the infected fraction of the population is partitioned between the two sink states (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{H}, \overline{E}&lt;/script&gt;) obviously depends on the IFR (note the logarithmic scale), as stated in \ref{SIHE_statsol_S}.
Note that while the IFR is ‘hard-wired’ in the parameter ratio &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\tau}{\tau+\lambda}&lt;/script&gt;, how much of the population gets infected and dies depends on &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt; and therefore &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt;, the rate constant for transmission. This is where physical distancing measures would intervene to choke off the flow &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;{S}\rightarrow{I}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us go now one step further and allow for a pre-symptomatic state, defining &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; as a variable of the infectious but pre-symptomatic state and adding a variable &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;(iling) that is the infectious and symptomatic state. Now the compartments of this ‘&lt;em&gt;SIAHE&lt;/em&gt;’ model and the flows between them are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/covid/SIAHE_res.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 4: ‘SIAHE’ SIR model with presymptomatic (&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;) and symptomatic (&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;) infectious state and two outcomes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By highlighting the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;{S}\rightarrow{I}&lt;/script&gt; flow in red I want to indicate that this is the (only) nonlinear term, and now this flow has two parameters as the ODE for &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; is:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{dS(t)}{dt} = -S(t)(\alpha I(t) + \gamma A(t))&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two bilinear terms are positive feedbacks on the otherwise linear system. If it wasn’t for these terms the system would have an equilibrium where only the &lt;a href=&quot;http://vcp.med.harvard.edu/papers/jg-lap-dyn.pdf&quot;&gt;terminal vertices&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H, E&lt;/script&gt;) of its graph can have nonzero value, just like with the equilibrium we have for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbkoltai.github.io/exastolog&quot;&gt;state transition graph of a stochastic Boolean model&lt;/a&gt;.
Because of this nonlinear feedback however &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; can (and usually does) also have a nonzero value in steady state, so the equilibrium of SIAHE is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(\overline{S},0,0,\overline{H},\overline{E})&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us again get the formula for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt;. Ff we have this, the rest of the system has linear kinetics, so the stationary values of &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt; will follow easily from the kinetic matrix of the IAHE variables. I follow here the derivation from the Nature Medicine article, except that it is for a simpler (5 variables) model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to introduce some notation:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
x(t){=}\begin{bmatrix} I(t) \\ A(t) \end{bmatrix},
c{=}\begin{bmatrix} \alpha \\ \gamma \\ \end{bmatrix},
b{=}\begin{bmatrix} 1 \\ 0 \end{bmatrix},
F{=}\begin{bmatrix} -(\lambda{+}\zeta)&amp;{0}\\{\zeta}&amp; -(\kappa{+}\tau) \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the ODE for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I(t)&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A(t)&lt;/script&gt; is:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\dot{x(t)}{=}F x(t) + b c^T x(t) S(t)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\dot{S}(t){=}-c^T x(t) S(t)&lt;/script&gt; we can substitute this in and get:  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\dot{x(t)}{=}F x(t) - b  \dot{S}(t)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then integrating (and changing &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi&lt;/script&gt;), for the left side:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\int_0^\infty \dot{x}(\phi) d\phi = x(\infty){-}x(0){=}-x(0)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and on the right hand side we have:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F\int_0^\infty x(\phi) d\phi - b \int_0^\infty \dot{S}(\phi) =
F\int_0^\infty x(\phi) d\phi - b(\overline{S}-S(0))&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so then we have:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-x(0){=}F\int_0^\infty x(\phi) d\phi - b(\overline{S}-S(0))&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if we pre-multiply by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c^T F^{-1}&lt;/script&gt; (a [1x2] vector) to get rid of F and to turn both sides into scalars we get:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-c^T F^{-1} x(0) =\int_0^\infty c^T x(\phi) d\phi - c^T F^{-1} b(\overline{S}-S(0))&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the ODE of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\dot{S}&lt;/script&gt; we can substitute &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\dot{S(t)}}{S(t)}&lt;/script&gt; into &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c^T x(t)&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-c^T F^{-1} x(0){=} - \int_0^\infty \frac{\dot{S}(\phi)}{S(\phi)} d\phi - c^T F^{-1} b(\overline{S}-S(0)) = log \frac{S(0)}{\overline{S}} - c^T F^{-1} b(\overline{S}-S(0))&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then after a rearrangement we have the solution for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\overline{S}&lt;/script&gt; in the same form as for the ‘&lt;em&gt;SIHE&lt;/em&gt;’ model in \ref{SIHE_statsol_S}:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-c^T F^{-1}b \overline{S} - log \overline{S} = -c^T F^{-1}b S(0) - log S(0) + c^T F^{-1} x(0)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-c^T F^{-1} b&lt;/script&gt; is the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0&lt;/script&gt; of this version of the model, so rewriting with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0 \overline{S}- log \overline{S} = R_0 S(0) - log S(0) + c^T F^{-1} x(0)
\tag{5}
\label{SIAHE_S_statsol_R0}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explicitly, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0&lt;/script&gt; is:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0{=}\frac{\alpha}{\lambda+\zeta}{+}\frac{\zeta \gamma}{(\kappa+\tau)(\lambda+\zeta)}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0&lt;/script&gt; is linearly increasing in the contagion rates &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt;, while decreasing in the rate constants of the outgoing flows of &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;, ie. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\kappa, \tau, \lambda&lt;/script&gt;.
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\zeta&lt;/script&gt; has a more complicated effect as it decreases the first term, but increases the second. This makes sense too, since this is the rate constant &lt;em&gt;between&lt;/em&gt; the two contagious states &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(to be continued…in progress)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-notes-on-the-literature&quot;&gt;&lt;ins&gt;2. Notes on the literature&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dynamical-models&quot;&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Dynamical models&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;school-closures-event-cancellations-and-the-mesoscopic-localization-of-epidemics-in-networks-with-higher-order-structure&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.05924.pdf&quot;&gt;School closures, event cancellations, and the mesoscopic localization of epidemics in networks with higher-order structure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Higher-order struct leads to mesoscopic localization (concentration into substructures).&lt;br /&gt;
Individuals classified by # of contacts:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_k&lt;/script&gt;: % susceptible with k contacts&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I_k&lt;/script&gt;: % infected with k contacts&lt;br /&gt;
Clique prevalence: average fraction of nodes within cliques of size &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/covid/clique%20prevalence.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does lower coupling mean?
There are two distributions that characterize the network:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g_m&lt;/script&gt;: membership of nodes. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_m&lt;/script&gt; is % of &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; with number &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; of memberships in higher order structures.  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g_m \sim m^{-\gamma}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
p_n: distribution of clique size &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_n \sim n^{-\gamma}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If edges are removed, in the localized network there is a critical size n_c for cliques under which if enough edges are removed, then there are no infections anymore in these cliques.
Also, in localized networks global prevalence falls off much more sharply with stronger intervention, whereas effect is linear in ‘delocalized’ networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variables are defined by master equations. This goes down after a week.
With active case finding the peak is lower and earlier.
With higher transmission rate this gets higher, converging to ~0.9.
But if structures are highly coupled (a), clique prevalence ~same for n [20,100].
With lower coupling (b) there is &lt;em&gt;mesoscopic localization&lt;/em&gt;: global prevalence can be very low, but within cliques, much higher % of infection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-contribution-of-pre-symptomatic-transmission-to-the-covid-19-outbreak&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cmmid.github.io/topics/covid19/control-measures/pre-symptomatic-transmission.html&quot;&gt;The Contribution of Pre-symptomatic Transmission to the COVID-19 Outbreak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimates that ~25% of transmission in Shenzhen was asymptomatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;temporal-variation-in-transmission-during-the-covid-19-outbreak-in-italy&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cmmid.github.io/topics/covid19/current-patterns-transmission/italy-time-varying-transmission.html&quot;&gt;Temporal variation in transmission during the COVID-19 outbreak in Italy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimates on reproduction numbers in regions of Italy. Started from 3-4, falling towards 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;substantial-undocumented-infection-facilitates-the-rapid-dissemination-of-novel-coronavirus-science-16-march&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/sci/early/2020/03/13/science.abb3221.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Substantial undocumented infection facilitates the rapid dissemination of novel coronavirus (SCIENCE, 16 March)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimates from a model + Bayesian inference.
Main findings (these are max probability estimates):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;86% of infections were from undocumented cases in China &lt;em&gt;before travel ban of 23/january&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;undocumented cases had 55% (mu*beta) transmission rate of documented ones (beta)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;undocumented cases were the source of 79% of documented cases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Model: dynamics of infections among 375 Chinese cities.
Spatial dynamics captured by # of passengers from city &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt;.
Variables for each city: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i, E_i, I_i^r, I_i^u&lt;/script&gt; (undocumented).
Simulations by ‘iterated filter-ensemble adjustment Kalman filter (IF-EAKF) framework’.&lt;br /&gt;
Inferred parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Z: average latent period&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;D: average duration of infection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu&lt;/script&gt;: transmission reduction factor for undocumented&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;beta: transmission rate for documented&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;alpha: fraction of documented infections&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;theta: travel multiplicative factor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reporting delay is included (from Gamma distribution).
Best-fitting parameter values identified by maximum likelihood.
They could distinguish between mu-alpha value pairs with different individual values but same product. They did simulations with all parameter value pairs (within certain range) and .
Delay of reporting crucial, this needs to be speeded up to stop the spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/covid/science_article_undocum_cases.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/sci/suppl/2020/03/13/science.abb3221.DC1/abb3221_Li_SM.pdf&quot;&gt;SI&lt;/a&gt; contains equations.
System of coupled ODEs: S_i is susceptibles in city &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;.
All terms normalised by total population (in that city).
D: &lt;duration infection=&quot;&quot;&gt;  
Then effective reproduction number $$R_e=\alpha \beta D + (1-\alpha)\mu \beta\ D$$&lt;/duration&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System of ODEs are then solved stochastically: each RHS term is sampled from a Poisson distribution. So we take the current value of the variable and then sample from a Poisson distribution (the deterministic value is the lambda of the Poisson). This is for each RHS term!
Initial prior ranges for parameters are from Latin Hypercube Sampling.
Initial values for populations similarly sampled (eg. initial exposed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the simulation results are mapped into reported cases by a separate delay model.
Delay is from a Gamma distribution approximated from data.
Movements between cities estimated from mobile apps: Tencent, Mobility Index from Baidu.
‘Iterated’ filtering to estimate model parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
#### [Wolfram Mathematica notebook on epidemic modeling](https://community.wolfram.com/groups/-/m/t/1896178)
https://www.twitch.tv/videos/569280246

#### [NECSI Slack channel for modeling](https://app.slack.com/client/T2DRR8UNB/CV19X1PKJ/thread/CUTSF2Q6R-1584495843.398200)
---&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;imperial-impact-of-non-pharmaceutical-interventions-npis-to-reduce-covid19-mortality-and-healthcare-demand-16-march&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/sph/ide/gida-fellowships/Imperial-College-COVID19-NPI-modelling-16-03-2020.pdf&quot;&gt;Imperial: Impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) to reduce COVID19 mortality and healthcare demand (16 March)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 strategies:
1) mitigation: can reduce peak healthcare demand by 2/3 and deaths by 50%. Still 100s of 1000s of deaths
2) Suppression: preferable for countries that can achieve. Means social distancing for &lt;em&gt;whole&lt;/em&gt; of the population. Need to be maintained until vaccine found, as there is rebound if interventions are targeted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individual-based simulation model. Mixing in different environments. Schools double per capita rate of contacts. Incubation time 5 days. Infectiousness starts before symptoms. R0: between 2 and 2.6. Individual infectiousness varies (gamma distribution).
Symptomatic cases self-isolate w 1 day delay. 5 day delay to hospitalisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no measures: peak after 3 months, 80% of US/UK population infected. 30-time more demand for critical care beds than available. 2.2M dead in US, 0.5M dead in UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mitigation: for 7 different levels of mitigation they make estimates for the reduction in peak bed demand and total deaths. For two values of R0 (2.2, 2.4) and 4 values of ‘triggers’ (cumulative ICU cases). Trigger means when policies (home quarantine etc) are switched on/off.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suppression: all measures combined can keep ICU bed demand below UK surge bed capacity (5K). Adaptive triggering of suppression: on-off with some thresholds for # of ICU cases.
Even with most comprehensive suppression strategy in 2 yrs abt 30K deaths in UK.
Higher ON trigger and/or lower OFF -&amp;gt; more deaths etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/pnas/105/12/4639.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Model used by Imperial from 2008&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;necsi-response-to-imperial-paper-ferguson-et-al-impact-of-non-pharmarceutical&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5b68a4e4a2772c2a206180a1/t/5e70eb32b16229792eb14836/1584458547530/ReviewOfFergusson.pdf&quot;&gt;NECSI response to Imperial paper (Ferguson et al) ‘Impact of non-pharmarceutical…’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They agree with Ferguson that suppression is needed to bring down R&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; below 1.
They disagree w Ferguson claim that 2nd outbreak unavoidable, because (according to NECSI) during lockdown infectious ppl can be identified and their contacts isolated.
Ferguson calculate new infections as fcn of infected % and immunity, but not the phase of trajectory (ergodicity).
Not true that resurgence starts from even 1 case, China data showed &lt;em&gt;only 5% of close contacts of infected tested positive&lt;/em&gt;. Small outbreaks can be controlled by testing.
Ferguson ignores super-spreader events by ignoring ‘fat tail distribution of contagion’.
But cutting off fat tail by banning events reduced &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0&lt;/script&gt;.
Ferguson use SIR ODE-model, not appropriate bc it ignores:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;local dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;non-normal distrib. of infection events per person (superspreaders)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dynamic or stochastic values for parameters (social response)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Imperial model has different environments and it is agent-based, so maybe this is not fair.
Debate on this on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yaneerbaryam/status/1239936951823843328&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;beyond-contact-tracing-community-based-early-detection-for-ebola-response-plos-currents-outbreaks-2016&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://necsi.edu/beyond-contact-tracing&quot;&gt;Beyond contact tracing: Community-based early detection for Ebola response, PLoS Currents Outbreaks (2016)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stochastic model by NECSI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;necsi-working-paper-eliminating-covid-19-a-community-based-analysis-19-march&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5b68a4e4a2772c2a206180a1/t/5e737b95403f772d8ce0e04a/1584626591711/CommunityPrevention.pdf&quot;&gt;NECSI Working Paper: Eliminating COVID-19. A Community-based Analysis (19 March)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NECSI probabilistic model. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_*&lt;/script&gt;: community transmission rate.
i_0_c: stochastic factor of initial foothold the virus gains in a community
i_c(t): # active infections in community &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If infection not contained, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;exp(r_c t)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt; community implements aggressive suppression policies.
Infections decay as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;exp(-t/\tau_c)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After intervention # of infections is:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i_c(t)=( i_c^0 exp(r_c T_c) ) exp(-(t-T_c)/\tau_c)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Community transmission &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sim i_c(t) p(travel)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Poisson process, average number of infected communities can be estimated by integrating the two sub-processes (until and after &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;
Calculate expected number of other communities infected by community &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
It’s assumed growth within one community is exponential until &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt; (intervention), then exponential decay after &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;social-contacts-and-mixing-patterns-relevant-to-the-spread-of-infectious-diseases-plos-medicine-2008&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article?id=10.1371/journal.pmed.0050074&quot;&gt;Social Contacts and Mixing Patterns Relevant to the Spread of Infectious Diseases (PLoS Medicine, 2008)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimates for mixing patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;an-investigation-of-transmission-control-measures-during-the-first-50-days-of-the-covid-19-epidemic-in-china-science-31-mar&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/early/2020/03/30/science.abb6105&quot;&gt;An investigation of transmission control measures during the first 50 days of the COVID-19 epidemic in China (Science, 31 Mar)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effect of Wuhan travel ban. Cities as variables in a SIR-like model, estimates on travel flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mers-basic-reproduction-number-biomed-eng-online-2017-1679&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://biomedical-engineering-online.biomedcentral.com/track/pdf/10.1186/s12938-017-0370-7&quot;&gt;MERS basic reproduction number (BioMed Eng OnLine (2017) 16:79)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authors fit SIR model to data, least-square fit, they find a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0&lt;/script&gt; around 8 (!).
How did they manage to suppress MERS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;uri-alon-adaptive-cyclic-exit-strategies-from-lockdown-medium-post-on-preprint-7-april&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@urialonw/adaptive-cyclic-exit-strategies-from-lockdown-to-suppress-covid-19-and-allow-economic-activity-4900a86b37c7&quot;&gt;Uri Alon: Adaptive cyclic exit strategies from lockdown (Medium post on preprint, 7 April)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 day work+10 day lockdown, antiphased for 2 groups of households.
Review of deterministic, stochastic and also &lt;em&gt;network&lt;/em&gt; SEIR model, different cyclic lockdown strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antiphasing (staggering) uses the timeline of the disease and infectiousness:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/770/0*MWxESwBV56QMF9rc&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;imperial-report-12-the-global-impact-of-covid-19-and-strategies-for-mitigation-and-suppression-26-march-2020&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/mrc-gida/2020-03-26-COVID19-Report-12.pdf&quot;&gt;Imperial: Report 12: The Global Impact of COVID-19 and Strategies for Mitigation and Suppression (26 March 2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global estimates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;without intervention&lt;/em&gt;: 7 billion infections and 40 millon deaths in 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;mitigation&lt;/em&gt;: with 60% reduction of social contacts, 20 million deaths avoided, all health care systems overwhelmed, in low income setting by factor of 25.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;suppression&lt;/em&gt;: 30-39 million deaths can be avoided (compared to no intervention strategy), depending on timing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Household size/structure is critical, differences result in different &lt;em&gt;attack rates&lt;/em&gt; by age groups. Number of hospital beds/1000 population from &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator?tab=all&quot;&gt;World Bank&lt;/a&gt;.
Estimates for 3 strategies of unmitigated, mitigation, mitigation+enhanced social distancing for elderly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hospitalisation rate: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sim&lt;/script&gt; 3%, 2%, 2% (esimates for difference world regions on Fig 4).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;critical care: 1%, 0.5%, 0.2%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;deaths: 0.6-0.8%, 0.4%, 0.2%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Despite higher rates of contact across older age-groups, we predict a lower incidence of severe
disease, hospitalisation and deaths in lower income settings. This is driven by the younger average age
of these populations.’ (Figure 5)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simulations for countries in different income groups: how ICU capacity would be exceeded under different suppression strategies and mitigation (Figure 6).
Table 1 summarizes estimates by regions. Two suppression scenarios with 0.2 and 1.6 deaths/100K population/week.
Unmitigated (world, total): 40M deaths, 1.9M deaths with suppression with trigger 0.2/100K pop/week, 10.4M with suppression with trigger 1.6/100K pop/week. Difference &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sim&lt;/script&gt; 5-fold between two suppression strategies in most regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Model is age-structured SIR-model incorporating demographic structure and rates of contact. Comorbidities not taken into account. Full model stochastic age-structured SEIR model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excel spreadsheet with results &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/sph/ide/gida-fellowships/Imperial-College-COVID19-Global-unmitigated-mitigated-suppression-scenarios.xlsx&quot;&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3730771#.XptEtZ9fir4&quot;&gt;Covid-data used by Imperial models (cited by other publication)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
```python
from scipy.integrate import odeint
import numpy as np
import matplotlib.pyplot as plt
%matplotlib inline
!pip install mpld3
import mpld3
mpld3.enable_notebook()
```
---&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;macroeconomics-of-epidemics&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kellogg.northwestern.edu/faculty/rebelo/htm/epidemics.pdf&quot;&gt;Macroeconomics of epidemics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interaction terms between economic variables and epidemiological ones are via consumption and work hour variables:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consumption: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\pi_1(S_t C_t^S) (I_t C_t^I)&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_t&lt;/script&gt; consumption spending&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\pi_2(S_t N_t^S) (I_t N_t^I)&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N_t&lt;/script&gt; is work hours
and a general term &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\pi_3 S_t I_t&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newly infected: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_t&lt;/script&gt;, therefore susceptibles: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_{t+1}=S_t - T_t&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Number of infected: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I_{t+1}=I_t + T_t - (\pi_r + \pi_d) I_t&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Zoonotic introduction of virus into population: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I_0{=}\epsilon,\ S_0{=}1{-}\epsilon&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do the epidemiological variables affect the economic ones?
Pre-epidemic, the population is made up of identical agents optimizing the utility function:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u(c_t,n_t)=ln(c_t) - \frac{\phi}{2} n_t^2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the outbreak we have the modified version of this utility function per compartments:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;U_t^j&lt;/script&gt;: ‘lifetime utility’ of agent &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;j&lt;/script&gt; (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;j=s,i,r&lt;/script&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agents have the budget constraint: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1+\mu_t)c_t^j=w_t \phi^j n_t^j + \Gamma_t&lt;/script&gt;
with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu_t&lt;/script&gt; tax on consumption, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w_t&lt;/script&gt; real wage, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi^j&lt;/script&gt; labour productivity, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi^j=1&lt;/script&gt; for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;j=s,r&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi^j{=}1&lt;/script&gt; for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;j{=}I&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Lifetime utility’ functions for compartments (subpopulations):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;S (susceptible): &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;U^s_t=u(c_t,n_t) + \beta [(1-\tau_t)U^s_{t+1} + \tau_t U^i_{t+1} ]&lt;/script&gt;, where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau_t&lt;/script&gt; is the probability that a susceptible person gets infected. This probability linearly increases with consumption and work, and the utilities of being susceptible or infected in next time step are inversely and proportionally scaled with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau_t&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;U^i_t&lt;/script&gt;: Similar lifetime utility function for infected people, but dependence only on recovery and death rates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First order conditions (first derivative equals 0) for consumption, work hours, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau_t&lt;/script&gt; calculated with Lagrange multipliers. Market clearing equilibrium for goods and labor, balanced gov. budget assumed (clearly not technically true, is this important?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To model healthcare collapse, quadratic dependence of mortality rate on total number of infected.
Treatment option introduces another parameter (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\delta_c&lt;/script&gt;) from infected to recovered, this is probability of a cure discovered in a time period.
Vaccine similarly modeled in utility function of susceptibles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping epidem. parameters from Ferguson (2006) onto model parameters: approx. 1/3, 1/3, 1/3 transmission in household, general community, schools and workplaces. From BLS Time Use Survey authors estimate % of time in buying things, eating outside, this gives estimate for consumption-related transmission.&lt;br /&gt;
Number of students and workers multiplied by estimates of contacts in those environments. This gives estimate for workplace transmission.
Labor productivity for infected people set to 80%, assuming 80% is asymptomatic (?) and those with symptoms do not work.&lt;br /&gt;
Peak of newly infected fraction of the population approximately 7% in the SIR (no utility functions) model.&lt;br /&gt;
In the SIR-Macro model infection impacts the economy by 1) reducing size of workforce 2) through the utility functions, households reduce their consumption and work hours. In turn, their reduced consumption/work decreases the probability of getting infected. Peak of infected lower (5%) at occurs later.
Recession is much more severe due to reduced consumption/work. If mortality rate depends on healthcare being overwhelmed, households absorb this effect via utility function by reducing their economic activity, exacerbating recession.
Vaccine or effective drugs have opposite effect, households cut back less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Containment measures are modeled as a tax on consumption. Optimization is done on how containment measures are introduced in time.
The model assumes that infections cannot be completely suppressed if no vaccine, until population immunity achieved. Therefore early strong containment has high economic cost but followed still by an outbreak. In this framework containment should be escalated gradually as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I&lt;/script&gt; grows. But China, Korea seems to show that suppression is possible. Costs of containment policies referred to as ‘Ramsey problem’: costs vs. maximizing social welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ‘smart containment’ scenario is also modeled where it is assumed that planners know the health status of everyone and can maximimize overall social utility by blocking all infected from working. In this case there is no cost to containment, but this requires perfect knowledge. Ie. huge social returns on testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;modeling-the-impact-of-social-distancing-testing-contact-tracing-and-household-quarantine-on-second-wave-scenarios-of-the-covid-19-epidemic-vespignani&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cosnet.bifi.es/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/main.pdf&quot;&gt;Modeling the impact of social distancing, testing, contact tracing and household quarantine on second-wave scenarios of the COVID-19 epidemic (Vespignani)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agent based model of Boston area, 85K agents (64K adults, 21K children). Compartments distinguish between asymptomatic and symptomatic.
Different reopening scenarios varying in testing and tracing efficiency, calculating peak incidences.
Data is from 6 months of anonymized survey.
Interactions modeled as a contact network with weights proportional to amount of time (normalised by total observation time) two agents spent in same location. 83K locations are defined (from Foursquare).
Weights within households (inversely) proportional to size of household.
Public space, schools, households three layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---###############################################################################################################################---&gt;
&lt;!---###############################################################################################################################---&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Tools&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;interactive-modeling-shiny-app&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alhill.shinyapps.io/COVID19seir/&quot;&gt;Interactive modeling (Shiny app)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an ODE model assuming complete homogeneity. Three &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; populations with different rates of transmission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shiny-app-of-sir-model-digital-contact-tracing-for-sars-cov-2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bdi-pathogens.shinyapps.io/covid-19-transmission-routes&quot;&gt;Shiny app of SIR model (Digital contact tracing for SARS-CoV-2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adjustable parameters, generates graphs interactively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;seirsplus-python-package-for-stochastic-and-network-based-seir-model&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ryansmcgee/seirsplus&quot;&gt;SEIRSPLUS: Python package for stochastic and network based SEIR model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python package to set up epidemiological models easily, used in Uri Alon study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;socialmixr-r-package-has-survey-data-on-mixing-patterns&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sbfnk/socialmixr&quot;&gt;SocialmixR R package has survey data on mixing patterns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey on France mixing patterns in &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0133203&quot;&gt;PloS ONE 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---##############################################################################################################################---&gt;
&lt;!---##############################################################################################################################---&gt;
&lt;!---##############################################################################################################################---&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-and-reports&quot;&gt;&lt;ins&gt;Data and reports&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;secondary-attack-rate-and-super-spreading-events-for-sars-cov-2-lancet-27-febr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/action/showPdf?pii=S0140-6736%2820%2930462-1&quot;&gt;Secondary attack rate and super-spreading events for SARS-CoV-2 (Lancet, 27 Febr)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimates for some ‘super-spreader’ events in table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;epidemiological-data-from-the-covid-19-outbreak-real-time-case-information&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41597-020-0448-0.pdf&quot;&gt;Epidemiological data from the COVID-19 outbreak, real-time case information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fundamental-principles-of-epidemic-spread-highlight-the-immediate-need-for-large-scale-serological-surveys-to-assess-the-stage-of-the-sars-cov-2-epidemic&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.03.24.20042291v1&quot;&gt;Fundamental principles of epidemic spread highlight the immediate need for large-scale serological surveys to assess the stage of the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;testing-everyone-instead-of-contact-tracing-sten-linnarsson-karolinska&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@sten.linnarsson/to-stop-covid-19-test-everyone-373fd80eb03b&quot;&gt;Testing everyone instead of contact tracing (Sten Linnarsson, Karolinska)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medium note on a preprint.
If &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;c\ p &gt; (R_0-1)/(R_0-R_q)&lt;/script&gt;, then exponential decay of outbreak. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_0&lt;/script&gt; ~ 2.4, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R_q&lt;/script&gt; ~ 0.3 (Wuhan estimate).
c: compliance to self-quarantine after testing positive&lt;br /&gt;
p: true positive rate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fastest test currently: RT-LAMP technology, 10-30 mins, based on RNA detection. Polymerase with reverse transcriptase activity amplifies viral RNA —&amp;gt; H+ release —&amp;gt; pH sensitive dye.
But: it requires 65C incubation (tap water?).
Alternatives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rolling circle replication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in vitro viral replication assays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lockdown cost dwarfs testing cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nn-taleb-tail-risk-of-contagious-diseases&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchers.one/media/documents/282-m-corona2.pdf&quot;&gt;NN Taleb: Tail Risk of Contagious Diseases&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-everyone-should-wear-a-mask&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@Cancerwarrior/covid-19-why-we-should-all-wear-masks-there-is-new-scientific-rationale-280e08ceee71&quot;&gt;Why everyone should wear a mask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;estimates-of-the-severity-of-coronavirus-disease-2019-a-model-based-analysis-lancet-30-march&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/laninf/article/PIIS1473-3099(20)30243-7/fulltext&quot;&gt;Estimates of the severity of coronavirus disease 2019: a model-based analysis (Lancet, 30 March)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimates on CFR and IFR from Hubei and China in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ihme-institute-for-health-metrics-and-evaluation-predictions-about-peaks&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.healthdata.org/covid/updates&quot;&gt;IHME (Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation) predictions about peaks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preds made 05 April are for France 15K deaths by August, UK 66K.
This was revised upwards to France (22.5K) and downwards for UK (37.5K).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparedness-and-vulnerability-of-african-countries-against-importations-of-covid-19-a-modelling-study&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/action/showPdf?pii=S0140-6736%2820%2930411-6&quot;&gt;Preparedness and vulnerability of African countries against importations of COVID-19: a modelling study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importation risk from China vs health care system capacity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ron-milo-covid-by-the-numbers-elife-updated-paper&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://elifesciences.org/articles/57309/&quot;&gt;Ron Milo: COVID by the numbers (eLife, updated paper)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimates on size, mutation rate, genome of virus.
Nucleotide identity with other coronaviruses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bat CoV: 96%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pangolin CoV: 91%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SARS-CoV-1: 80%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MERS: 55%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;common cold CoV: 50%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-early-phase-of-the-covid-19-outbreak-in-lombardy-italy-20-mar-arxiv&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.09320&quot;&gt;The early phase of the COVID-19 outbreak in Lombardy, Italy (20 Mar, arXiv)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early estimates on epidemic in Lombardy (hospitalisation, intensive care, deaths), arguing for aggressive containment strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tomas-pueyo-the-hammer-and-the-dance-medium-19-march&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@tomaspueyo/coronavirus-the-hammer-and-the-dance-be9337092b56&quot;&gt;Tomas Pueyo: The hammer and the dance (Medium, 19 March)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uses simple SIR model to argue why suppression is needed, as mitigation leads to enormous death toll (some estimates on side-effects).
Suppression buys time for producing equipment, maybe drugs.
Not original research, but summarizes Imperial’s 16 March study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cluster-of-covid-19-in-northern-france-a-retrospective-closed-cohort-study&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.04.18.20071134v1.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Cluster of COVID-19 in northern France: A retrospective closed cohort study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oise heavily exposed to SARS-CoV-2. Infection attack rate (IAR) from antibody detection.
171/661 had antibodies, &lt;strong&gt;26% IAR&lt;/strong&gt;, 0% IFR (fatality). Hospitalisation rate 5%.
Anosmia (smell blindness) and ageusia (loss of taste) good predictors of infection.
IAR for smokers 7% vs. 28% (smoking: 75% decrease in risk of infection). Asymptomatic infections 17%.
High school: 41% IAR, among parents only 10%. 661 participants in total. Median age 37, 38% male. 40% age 15-17, only 2 people over 65. Secondary IAR in households 10-11% (both for parents and siblings). In Shenzhen similar study found 15%.
ELISA antibody tests were also made on blood samples of blood donors in the area, 3% IAR.
Oise was one of the early epicenters of the epidemic in France and these numbers are results of period before lockdown. Low prevalence numbers suggest herd immunity cannot be quickly established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;animal-passage-experiments-and-possibility-of-accidental-escape&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newsweek.com/controversial-wuhan-lab-experiments-that-may-have-started-coronavirus-pandemic-1500503&quot;&gt;Animal passage experiments and possibility of accidental escape&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Description of animal passage experiments (with ferrets) since 2011. PREDICT program. No evidence of such experiments in Wuhan lab.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="epidemics" /><category term="complex-systems" /><category term="covid19" /><summary type="html">General properties, not predictions</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1990-2020, the false dawn of globalization?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/illusion-globalisation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1990-2020, the false dawn of globalization?" /><published>2020-02-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-02-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/illusion-globalisation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/illusion-globalisation/">&lt;p&gt;As the coronavirus is spreading through the world I have been gradually overcome by a feeling similar to the moment when an optical shift occurs. If you have looked at a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Random_dot_stereogram&quot;&gt;stereogram&lt;/a&gt;, you know what I mean: out of random dots a three dimensional pattern emerges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost irrespectively of political taste, most of us, at least in middle and high-income countries, have experienced these last decades of expanding world trade, cheapening travel, instantaneous communication and product availability as a never-ending ahistorical present, a normality taken for granted. In reality maybe it was a very fragile and unsustainable experiment, about to be swept away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have lived my whole life in the era after the fall of the Soviet Union, a monotone steady-state of globalized consumer capitalism, unchallenged as a system. Obviously, in many world regions the period has been anything but steady - it meant almost permanent war in the Middle East, and periods of violence in the Balkans, Ukraine, parts of Africa etc. The 2008 crash, the following gradual implosion of the political center and rise of right-wing populism to electoral victories (2010: Hungary, 2014: India, 2015: Poland, 2016: US &amp;amp; Brexit, 2018: Brazil) signaled a general shift in the management of global capitalism.
Still, the characterizations of ‘globalized’ and unchallenged as a system still stand.
If the era is to be summed up in one word it is probably ‘globalization’.
Now it feels like an infinity since we have been ‘globalized’, doesn’t it?
It is easy to miss just how condensed this process has been in time. To see that, it is helpful to zoom out a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The explosion in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_population_estimates&quot;&gt;world population&lt;/a&gt; predates globalization and was a slower process.
But it has also almost completely happened in the last century and especially its second half. Most estimates put the global population between 200-300 million at the time of AD 1.&lt;br /&gt;
It stayed nearly flat until 1500, when it reached half a billion.&lt;br /&gt;
It took &lt;em&gt;three centuries&lt;/em&gt; for the global population to double again to reach one billion around 1820.
Then it doubles again in a century, reaching 2 billion by 1930.&lt;br /&gt;
But then the dynamics changes: 3 billion by 1960 (30 years to grow by a billion), 4 billion by 1974 (14 years), 5 billion by 1987 (12 years), 6 billion by 1999 (12 years), 7 billion in 2011 (12 years).&lt;br /&gt;
The increase over the last two thousand years is from 0.3 to 7.5 billion. That growth is extremely condensed in time: 90% of it happened in the last 10% (two hundred years) of this period, and almost 80% in just the last century. A bit more than half of the entire increase (from 3.7 to 7.5 billion) happened in the last 50 years. That is just the last 2% of the AD era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economic growth is even more concentrated. Most human activity in pre-capitalist, pre-industrial societies did not take the form of commodity production, of goods produced to be sold in exchange for money.
Therefore projecting back monetary estimates of world GDP before the 19th century is not to be taken literally, ie. these estimates do not correspond to money incomes or ‘value added’ (and realized in sale), as most human effort did not lead to any sale or payment of a wage.
Still, the rough estimates by Angus Maddison &lt;a href=&quot;#maddison2007world&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, Brad De Long &lt;a href=&quot;#delong1998estimating&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; and others give some ballpark figures for the total amount of human work performed on the planet. From the 19th century on they can be viewed increasingly as estimates of ‘economic’ activity, ie. all activity followed by monetary exchange.&lt;br /&gt;
Until technology comes into the picture, physical output should move together with the population size.
That is roughly what happens: according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://delong.typepad.com/print/20061012_LRWGDP.pdf&quot;&gt;DeLong’s estimates&lt;/a&gt; ‘gross world product’ grows threefold in the fifteen hundred years from 1 AD to 1500, from around 20 billion &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_dollar&quot;&gt;1990 US dollars&lt;/a&gt; (Int$) to 60 billion. (Again, this is a counterfactual: if the things made back then had been all for sale and could be bought with US dollars from 1990 by fixing their purchasing power.)&lt;br /&gt;
Similarly to population, it takes another three centuries to triple to 175 billion in 1800.&lt;br /&gt;
From that time point the effect of industrial technology becomes visible in the numbers.
Output doubles in 50 years by 1850 (360 billion), then triples to 1.1 trillion in another half a century by 1900. Another doubling comes in a &lt;em&gt;quarter&lt;/em&gt; of a century by 1925 (2 trillion) and yet another by 1950 (4 trillion) despite the destruction of the Great Depression and the Second World War.
With the post-war boom the doubling time becomes little more than a decade: it passes 8 trillion (8e12) in the early sixties, 15 trillion by the mid-70s, 30 trillion in the early nineties. The current world GDP of 80 trillion USD is approximately 60 trillion Int$ (1990 US dollars).&lt;br /&gt;
Altogether, in two thousand years there is an increase in yearly ‘gross world product’ from something like 0.02 trillion to 60 trillion.
Of this approximately 60 trillion total increase 59 trillion, that is &lt;em&gt;more than 98% has occurred in just the last one hundred years&lt;/em&gt;, the last 5% period of these two millennia. Recall, for population ‘just’ 80% of the total increase is concentrated in the same period.
But even within that period there is a further condensation into the post-war period, as more than &lt;em&gt;90% of all economic growth happened since 1950 and around half of it in the last 30 years&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
In short, when it comes to economic growth in aggregate numbers, almost all of it has been since the end of the Second World War. &lt;sup id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#myfootnote1&quot;&gt;(a)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Clearly the population increase was enabled and caused by industrialization and urbanization and with an expanding work force fed back into the growth of physical output, itself immensely amplified by cheap energy (fossil fuels) and technology.
Global population increased ‘only’ around 5-fold since 1900 (from 1.6 to the current 7.5 billion), in contrast to a 50-60-fold increase in economic output.
An order of magnitude difference accounted for by the 10-fold increase in per capita output. This is looking at the averages: in fact that growth was also geographically concentrated (although gradually less so from the 1970s with the growth of East Asian economies) so per capita output growth has been even steeper in some countries.&lt;br /&gt;
Economic growth is a second-order process on the back of population growth. The two mutually amplify each other and the former internally amplifies itself via technological development.
Economic growth is much faster, as the total output is population times per capita output, both on an upward trend that can be fit by exponentials. An average yearly growth rate of 1.4% roughly generates the 5-fold increase (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1.014^{120}{\approx}5&lt;/script&gt;) in 120 years (population), and 1.9% yields a 10-fold increase (per capita output).
The two of them combined into the 3-3.5% average growth rate of total output over the last 120 years when almost all (98%) economic growth has occurred in the history of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Globalization is then third-order: it is the network of connections between the hotspots of industrial production, the flow of goods, money, people and information.
It’s a process that starts at a higher level of differentiation and requires even more complex legal, infrastructural and communicational structures than production and exchange at a given location, or within a region or nation state.
&lt;em&gt;A priori&lt;/em&gt; then it would be logical that it is even more compressed in time.&lt;br /&gt;
In the 1990s with the growing globalization literature there were anecdotic or more serious attempts to dismiss the scale of the phenomenon by referring to the ‘first globalization’ from the late nineteenth century until the Great Depression.
Looking at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cepii.fr/cepii/en/bdd_modele/presentation.asp?id=32&quot;&gt;exports as a percentage of global GDP&lt;/a&gt; this seems true at first sight, comparing the period 1870-1930 to 1930-1970: the exports/GDP ratio exceeded 10% in 1871, hovering slightly above that level until 1930, from where it crashed back to 5% by 1935, first exceeding 10% again in 1973.
But these are percentage figures and meanwhile the world economy grew enormously.
So 10% of world GDP in 1871 and 1973 mean completely different things: the figure in 1973 &lt;em&gt;refers to a 35-times larger volume of exported goods&lt;/em&gt;, almost two orders of magnitude more. &lt;sup id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#myfootnote2&quot;&gt;(b)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These two moments of economic history are on very different levels of globalization.&lt;br /&gt;
But the bulk of the globalization process only starts from the early 1980s. There is a first burst of the exports-to-GDP ratio from 10% to 15-17% from 1973 to the mid-1980s. But then it shoots up to 30% of global GDP by 2008, dented by the financial crisis, again standing at 30% last year.
In absolute terms, &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/topic/trade&quot;&gt;global merchandise exports&lt;/a&gt; have grown about 60-fold since 1970, 10-fold since 1980 and 5-fold since 1990. As expected, this is even faster than the growth of global GDP (25-, 8- and 4-fold since the same dates, respectively).
Looking at sub-processes such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/ST.INT.XPND.CD&quot;&gt;international tourism&lt;/a&gt; (expenditures, 1995-2018: 4-fold increase), total volume of &lt;a href=&quot;https://unctad.org/en/Pages/DIAE/World%20Investment%20Report/Annex-Tables.aspx&quot;&gt;foreign direct investment&lt;/a&gt; (1990-2018: 6-fold increase), &lt;a href=&quot;https://unctad.org/Sections/dite_dir/docs/WIR2019/WIR19_tab04.xlsx&quot;&gt;the stock of foreign direct investment (FDI)&lt;/a&gt; (1990-2018: 14-fold increase), cross-border acquisitions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://unctad.org/Sections/dite_dir/docs/WIR2019/WIR19_tab10.xlsx&quot;&gt;cross border M&amp;amp;A purchases&lt;/a&gt;, 1990-2018: 9-fold increase) the growth is even more massive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot below highlights this concentration of the three exponential waves of population growth, economic growth and globalization into the last two centuries. To see the lags between economic growth and globalization we need to zoom in on these last two centuries, shown by the two insets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/illusionglob/world_pop_gdp_exports_log_yaxis_2insets_textboxes.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the last 30-40 years saw the volume of most kinds of international transactions multiply several fold.
But I feel these numbers still understate the actual impact on everyday life. Lifestyle has changed fundamentally too.&lt;br /&gt;
Low cost airlines have proliferated and reduced the cost of air travel dramatically, increasing total passenger number &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/IS.AIR.PSGR&quot;&gt;4-fold since 1990, to 4 billion&lt;/a&gt;.
At least in the core countries, flying no longer has much of a class distinction, something reserved for managerial elites. Almost everyone travels and flying to a sea resort in the summer is a must-do for many wage-workers.&lt;br /&gt;
With Amazon and others virtually any commodity has become instantaneously available.
Impatient consumers live-track deliveries of goods shipped in from the other side of the world, expected within days or even hours, thanks to burgeoning warehouse and delivery systems that seem to have replaced much of manufacturing employment in the West.&lt;br /&gt;
Exchanges in higher education have grown enormously, there are close to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/372900/number-of-chinese-students-that-study-in-the-us&quot;&gt;0.4 million Chinese students&lt;/a&gt; now studying at US universities.
PhD programs have proliferated, in the sciences mostly populated by foreigners from poorer countries, creating a new technocratic class of precarious, uprooted research workers (I’m one of them) jumping between temporary (postdoc) positions and countries, often barely speaking the local language and with tenuous links to the host society, but as a mass of people becoming integral to the research infrastructure of high-income countries.&lt;br /&gt;
Tens of millions of people moved to another country for work in the EU. Chinese migrant workers might be an order of magnitude more numerous, drawn to the coastal cities from the 1980s on by manufacturing jobs producing for Western and now global consumer markets.&lt;br /&gt;
Finally, the number of internet users has grown from 0.4 in 2000 to 4.5 billion this year which means almost the entire global adult population of &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.POP.1564.TO&quot;&gt;5 billion people&lt;/a&gt; has some access to it. Financial transactions, trade of physical goods, international travel, science, mass entertainment and increasingly interpersonal relationships are all built on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheap travel, mass international (or long-distance regional) mobility of workers, fast and universal availability of goods produced by global value chains, instantaneous and continuous exchange of data and communication: these have become the basic matrix of life, even if in very different forms, depending which end of globalization one is at - a web designer of a multinational fashion company in Germany and its seamstresses in Honduras or China live in different realities. Still, they were drawn into the same process, and all this happened very recently.&lt;br /&gt;
Commodity production, wage labor and monetary exchange have only become the dominant forms of social reproduction in the last 100-150 years in the wealthy countries, and in much of the world only in the last 30-50 years.
Massive global interconnectedness of the system of commodity production, globalization, really only emerged from the 1970s and especially from the late 1980s on.
This is a tiny subperiod within not only human history, but even ‘modern history’ since the onset of European colonialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are under 40 this is the only history (or lack thereof) you know first-hand. Attempts at reviving radical left or social-democratic politics have (eventually and/or so far) failed and no systemic challenges have appeared on the horizon. Bloody regional wars have been launched or ignited, mainly by the leading military power (the US). Much smaller scale, but more widely covered, terrorism has appeared in the core countries, but its ideologies (Islamist and white supremacist) did not offer a systemic alternative or a revolutionary politics. On the contrary, the terror acts were perpetrated in the name of revenge and a desperate conservative rejection of the present without any serious vision of an alternative future.
Overall, these disruptions did not question the tacit or explicit assumption that globalization simply cannot stop. It has become our unquestioned normality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus epidemic/pandemic, the stark facts of climate change becoming undeniable (and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v41/n15/francis-gooding/all-the-news-is-bad&quot;&gt;far worse than previously thought to be&lt;/a&gt;) and the near-total (and incidentally well-deserved) implosion of the political center in almost all major countries makes me wonder.
Was this all an illusion and, on a world historical scale, a very ephemeral one?
Globalization has stretched global value chains and networks of travel, communication and exchange enormously in a very short period, pushing many of these networks probably operating close to their breaking point.
The global corporations running them have surely implemented feedback mechanisms to cope with perturbations, to ensure profits keep flowing.
But there is a growing impression that the safety mechanisms that exist might be &lt;a href=&quot;https://necsi.edu/an-introduction-to-complex-systems-science-and-its-applications&quot;&gt;mismatched&lt;/a&gt; with respect to traumatic events such as a pandemic by &lt;em&gt;orders of magnitude&lt;/em&gt;.
They can presumably deal with small perturbations: there is excess demand or a failure here, a fire in a warehouse or a failed bridge there. These are small clogs in huge systems of circulation, blocking one channel, quickly dealt with or compensated by others.
They happen on the micro-scale of the system, at the level of its small components, and the size of such events should be normally distributed.
Events like epidemics are systemic: they are on the scale of the entire system. They are very unlikely but if they do happen, since the system’s components are interdependent, they can spread through it with enormous speed.
Almost all electronics and clothing is produced in Asia: if a whole province in China is under lockdown, this can cripple the tech giants whose gadgets everyone uses. Europe has a shortage of masks and not much textile industry left (this in itself can be presumably solved, but look at the pattern). In any Italian hotel there are probably a few cancellations every month - but now more than 90% of visitors cancel.
The expansion of air travel made it very hard or impossible to stop the spread of a virus, but globalization can hardly work without it. The interventions probably required to radically reduce the connectivity of the system in order to stop propagation might lead to a global slump: once the chain of defaults and bankruptcies spread, there is no fast way back to the growth path before the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speculative but not unreasonable question arises: have the last 30 years of globalization built up an unstable system hyper-connected by fragile networks, that inevitably generates critical events that it cannot deal with?
First, in a macroeconomic sense: the two long business cycles when globalization exploded, 1992-2000 and 2001-2008 were driven to an unprecedented degree by the expansion of private debt (&lt;a href=&quot;https://tradingeconomics.com/united-states/households-debt-to-gdp&quot;&gt;household&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/NCBDBIA027N&quot;&gt;corporate&lt;/a&gt; and especially within the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalreserve.gov/releases/z1/20191212/html/d3.htm&quot;&gt;financial&lt;/a&gt; sector) and asset inflation (stocks in the 1990s; real estate and securitized assets from mortgages/consumer debt in 2000s), at least in Western Europe and the United States. The fuel of the process that made it possible was also its own poison: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalreserve.gov/releases/z1/20191212/html/d1.htm&quot;&gt;5-15% yearly growth in debt&lt;/a&gt; could not be serviced by economies growing at 3% and most households with stagnant incomes.
At some point the chain had to break and securitization had ensured the toxic debt was scattered through the entire global financial system causing a systemic shock. The recapitalization of the banking system by the major states that followed, without significant financial reform, but austerity policies for the general population, destroyed the credibility of the technocratic/free-market political center that had managed the ‘golden years of globalization’ 1990-2008. The breakdown of political legitimacy to the point of ungovernability (Italy, Spain) and the ensuing nativist/far-right revolt that once in power started to question, withdraw from or even dismantle the multilateral systems (trade agreements, UN organizations, the EU) of globalization is another systemic shock.&lt;br /&gt;
Even more significantly, the exponential expansion of fossil fuel-based production across the globe has had the same temporal profile in terms of its energy use as in its growth counted in dollars.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdiac.ess-dive.lbl.gov/trends/emis/tre_glob.html&quot;&gt;Around half of all &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;CO_2&lt;/script&gt; emissions&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#wallace2020uninhabitable&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; by humanity (around 800 out of 1600 Gigatons) has occurred in the exact same period, the last 30 years, and 85% since WWII.
Incredibly, during 30 years of globalization as much of the Earth’s energy reservoir (condensed into the deposits of fossil fuel) was burnt up as in all human history before, unleashing a warming process that now, all evidence suggests, is almost impossible to stop from reaching a catastrophic 3 or 4 centigrades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are not small-scale events that the safety mechanisms of global value chains, transportation networks etc. are designed to deal with. They can instead remove their basis as the effects rapidly spread through the same networks. I do not know whether the current coronavirus epidemic can still be stopped or mitigated so that it does not reach a critical level.&lt;br /&gt;
But however this particular event turns out, it raises deeply alarming questions.
In the 1990s the early ideologues of globalization suggested the world has entered a perennial ‘end of history’ scenario of abundance and connectivity. Almost nobody believes that in 2020, but that is the least of it.
Instead what we might be facing is that the whole epoch of globalization was an ephemeral blip, and its inevitability an illusion, about to be swept away by the more powerful forces of epidemics, climate change, resource scarcity and the political turbulence and violence they generate.&lt;br /&gt;
This is a possibility, not a certainty and even if things go that way, it should not be imagined in a binary fashion. It is tempting to connect all the data points of crisis situations into an overall ‘collapsitarian’ narrative and prophylactically fantasize about ‘collapse’ or ‘the event’, after which ‘it will be over’.
This is an emotional reaction of preventive despair, but in reality the global economy cannot just disappear overnight, as it has massive inertia, technology and vested interests backed up by state power on its side to keep it going.
It is possible, though by now difficult to see how, that the current epidemic will be brought under control before it infects say 10% of the global population and becomes endemic.
Similarly, by a massive interventionist turn (along the lines of a Green New Deal) to decarbonize the economic system and invest in carbon capture technologies and reforestation to sequester the CO2 already in the atmosphere global warming could still be slowed down, so it does not exceed 2C by 2100. For this &lt;em&gt;yearly&lt;/em&gt; emission reductions of 5-10% would be needed, not a &lt;em&gt;growth&lt;/em&gt; of emissions as it is happening currently.
Within a best case scenario of moderate warming, its effects could be mitigated by extensive urban planning (relocation), infrastructure (water) and health care investment, so they are not disproportionately concentrated in the geographic regions and social strata with the least resources. In this scenario a window of opportunity could still be open for new technologies to overcome resource constraints and globalization to continue apace on the way to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2019/may/29/fully-automated-luxury-communism-aaron-bastani-review&quot;&gt;post-scarcity society&lt;/a&gt;. This passage is not completely barred, but at the very least, seems a more and more unlikely best case scenario than a safe bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose however that the best case scenario is no longer there and globalization, as we know it, is about to undergo some form of involution. The most immediate and disturbing question for those of us shaped and defined by this era is perhaps not even the usual ‘what do we do?’, but a more elementary one: if we cannot be citizens of the global village of eternal progress anymore, who are we going to be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;maddison2007world&quot;&gt;[1]A. Maddison, &lt;i&gt;The world economy volume 1 - A millennial perspective, volume 2 - Historical statistics&lt;/i&gt;. Academic Foundation, 2007. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;delong1998estimating&quot;&gt;[2]J. B. DeLong, “Estimating world GDP, one million BC–present,” &lt;i&gt;Draft paper. Berkeley, California&lt;/i&gt;, 1998. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wallace2020uninhabitable&quot;&gt;[3]D. Wallace-Wells, &lt;i&gt;The uninhabitable earth. Life after warming&lt;/i&gt;. Tim Duggan Books, 2020. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;myfootnote1&quot;&gt;(a)&lt;/a&gt; GDP is a ‘flow’ measure: it’s a rate, not a stock, so this is not the cumulative amount of capital stock built up, but the level of economic activity per year. &lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;myfootnote2&quot;&gt;(b)&lt;/a&gt; Additionally, in 1871 most ‘economic’ activity in the world was still outside the monetary economy so the estimate for world GDP, the denominator in the ratio, might be an underestimation, although I think Maddison etc. tried to account for this. &lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="political-economy" /><category term="globalization" /><category term="climate-change" /><category term="complex-systems" /><category term="ecology" /><category term="epidemics" /><category term="covid19" /><summary type="html">Climate change, epidemics and fascism could end globalization</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Generating multistability by coupling self-activating genes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/multistable/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Generating multistability by coupling self-activating genes" /><published>2019-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/multistable</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/multistable/">&lt;!---This [repository](https://github.com/mbkoltai/multistable_coupled_toggle) contains MATLAB scripts to model the stationary and dynamical behavior of ---&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I want to explore how we can generate a regulatory system that has several (more than 2) fixed points by coupling self-activating genes. It is an expanded model of a toggle switch &lt;a href=&quot;#gardner2000construction&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;: two genes (variables) that inhibit each other but also have nonlinear self-activation.
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/multistable_coupled_toggle&quot;&gt;scripts I wrote in MATLAB&lt;/a&gt; define a highly abstract, ordinary differential equation (ODE) model that does not describe stochastic fluctuations or the details of the underlying biochemical processes (transcription, translation, folding etc), as my interest here was to model multistable behavior in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My idea (coming from this &lt;a href=&quot;#lu2013tristability&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; paper) was that if the genes are bistable on their own then their nullclines can have 9 intersection points, ie. the two-dimensional systems when these genes are coupled can have up to 4 stable fixed points. Imagine two ‘S’ letters, one aligned with the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x&lt;/script&gt; axis, the other with the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y&lt;/script&gt; axis - how many times can they intersect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the main script &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/multistable_coupled_toggle/blob/master/multistable.m&quot;&gt;multistable.m&lt;/a&gt; we can first experiment with the parameters of a single self-activating gene: the cooperativity parameter (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n&lt;/script&gt;), the threshold of activation (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;K&lt;/script&gt;) and the rate of basal activation (transcription/translation) of the gene (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{\beta}&lt;/script&gt;). The ODE for a single gene is:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{dx(t)}{dt} = \beta + \frac{x(t)^n}{x(t)^n + K^n} - x(t)
\tag{1}\label{ode_autoact}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I am not assigning specific units to the variables and parameters, it is interesting to note what their dimensions are.&lt;br /&gt;
The differential equation describes a &lt;em&gt;rate&lt;/em&gt;, a change of concentration (mass per unit of volume) per unit of time, so it has to have a dimension of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;CT^{-1}&lt;/script&gt; (C: concentration, T: time).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta&lt;/script&gt; also has dimension of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;CT^{-1}&lt;/script&gt;. The state variable &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x(t)&lt;/script&gt; refers to the concentration of the gene product so its dimension is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C&lt;/script&gt; (concentration) and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;K&lt;/script&gt; must have the same dimension.&lt;br /&gt;
Then, strictly speaking the second term is dimensionless and would need to have a rate constant with dimension of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;CT^{-1}&lt;/script&gt; and the last term a rate constant with dimension of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T^{-1}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Since in practice these parameters only scale the production and degradation processes I am dropping them. This could be interpreted, if we are keen on dimensional consistency, as assuming their value is one, or that all other terms were divided by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We choose the values of these parameters as, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-MATLAB&quot;&gt;k_val=3/4; % threshold (50% of maximal rate)
beta_vals = [0 1e-3 linspace(0.01,k_val,100)]; % range of values for basal rate
n_vals=[2:5 8 10]; % % range of values for cooperativity
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then run the calculation by calling the function &lt;em&gt;fcn_bistab_roots&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-MATLAB&quot;&gt;[roots_real_nonnegat_matr,roots_all] = fcn_bistab_roots(beta_vals,n_vals,k_val);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am solving here only for the stationary solution (steady state, fixed points) I am not numerically solving the ODE. Instead, within &lt;em&gt;fcn_bistab_roots&lt;/em&gt;, I solve eq. \ref{ode_autoact} by setting the left hand side to 0 and rearranging the equation into polynomial form, which is:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x (x^n + K^n) - \beta (x^n + K^n) - x^n = x^{n+1} - (1 + \beta) x^n + K^n x - \beta K^n = 0&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x&lt;/script&gt; here stands for the stationary value of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;x(t)&lt;/script&gt;.
I solve this polynomial with MATLAB’s root-finding algorithm &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;root&lt;/script&gt;.
There cannot be more than 3 real and nonnegative roots of this polynomial, these physically relevant roots are contained in the matrix &lt;em&gt;roots_real_nonnegat_matr&lt;/em&gt; for the  parameter sets we generated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote two functions to visualize the solutions as a function of the basal production rate &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta&lt;/script&gt;.
With &lt;em&gt;fcn_plot_bifurc_diff_n_heatmap&lt;/em&gt; we can visualize the results as heatmaps on separate subplots for the different values of the nonlinearity (cooperativity) parameter &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-MATLAB&quot;&gt;fcn_plot_bifurc_diff_n_heatmap(beta_vals, n_vals, k_val, roots_real_nonnegat_matr)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bifurc_heatmaps_autostim.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1. Heatmaps showing the fixed points of a self-activating gene at different values of the cooperativity parameter. There are three bands corresponding to the three possible fixed points.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or as lineplots where the unstable fixed points are shown by the red dotted lines, called by the command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-MATLAB&quot;&gt;fcn_plot_bifurc_diff_n(roots_real_nonnegat_matr, beta_vals, n_vals,k_val,plot_pars)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and producing these plots:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bifurc_plots_autostim.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2. Bifurcation plots for a self-activating gene at different values of the cooperativity parameter. Blue lines are stable fixed points, dashed red lines are unstable.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lower threshold for the bistable range goes down while its extension grows with an increasing nonlinearity of the auto-activation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as it was shown by one of the first landmark papers &lt;a href=&quot;#gardner2000construction&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;http://vcp.med.harvard.edu/timeline.html&quot;&gt;modern&lt;/a&gt; (&amp;gt;2000) systems biology how two genes mutually inhibiting each other can lead to bistable behavior if the inhibition has a nonlinear (sigmoidal effect).
In this &lt;a href=&quot;#lu2013tristability&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; paper it was pointed out that if the auto-activation of these two genes already makes them bistable then coupling them can generate several stable fixed points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To intuitively illustrate this point, before setting up a model, let’s call the two genes A and B and we visualize their nullclines as a function of the value of the other gene.
Note that as we analyze the system in 2D now the basal production rate is a single value, we are not scanning through a range of values.
Where the two nullclines intersect we have a global fixed point: both variables have 0 time derivatives at these intersection points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/drawing_nullclines.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3: Sketch of intersecting nullclines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can have up to 9 intersection points and 4 of them can be intersections of the stable branches of the nullclines, shown by the green circles, so these will be stable fixed points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I implemented this two-dimensional system with adjustable parameters in MATLAB. First, I calculate the nullclines by polynomial root-finding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equations for the two genes are:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{dA}{dt} = \beta_A + f_A (1 + f_{BA}) - A&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{dB}{dt} = \beta_B + f_B (1 + f_{AB}) - B&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f_A&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f_B&lt;/script&gt; are the self-activation functions, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f_{BA}&lt;/script&gt; is the inhibition mechanism from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f_{AB}&lt;/script&gt; vice versa. The basal production terms and the decay terms are as in eq. \ref{ode_autoact}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expanding the activation and inhibition functions the full equations are:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{dA}{dt} = \beta_A + \frac{A^n}{ A^n + k_{AA}^n } (1 + \frac{k_{BA}^n}{k_{BA}^n + B^n}) - A&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{dB}{dt} = \beta_B + \frac{B^n}{ B^n + k_{BB}^n } (1 + \frac{k_{AB}^n}{k_{AB}^n + A^n} ) - B&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, since we are (first) solving for the stationary solutions we can rearrange the equations to polynomial form and for each equation treat the other variable as a parameter to calculate the nullclines.
This is done by calling the function &lt;em&gt;fcn_nullclines_double_inhib&lt;/em&gt;. We need to specify the range of values for the two variables where the nullclines are calculated and also the six parameters &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;[n,k_{AA},k_{BA},\beta_a,k_{BB},k_{AB},\beta_b]&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-MATLAB&quot;&gt;n=4;
kAA=3/4; kBB=3/4;
beta_a=1/4; beta_b=1/4;
kBA=1/2; kAB=1/2;
params = [n,kAA,kBA,beta_a,kBB,kAB,beta_b];
maxval_B=2.25; logvals=logspace(-2,log10(maxval_B),200);
linvals=linspace(0.01,maxval_B,300);
B_vals=[0 linvals]; A_vals=[0 linvals];
[real_nonnegroots_f1,real_nonnegroots_f2] = fcn_nullclines_double_inhib(A_vals,B_vals,params);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polynomial rootfinding is rather fast, for 200 input values, the calculation takes 35 seconds on my laptop (CPU @ 2.50GHz, 2601 Mhz, 2 Core(s)).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we can visualize the nullclines and their intersections that are the fixed points of the model by the function &lt;em&gt;fcn_plot_double_inhib&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-MATLAB&quot;&gt;parnames='$[n, k_{AA}, k_{BA},\beta_a, k_{BB},k_{AB},\beta_b]=$';
legend_str={'dA/dt=0,stable','dA/dt=0,unstable','dA/dt=0,stable'};
plot_pars={22,3,5,parnames,legend_str,0.02};
fcn_plot_double_inhib(B_vals,real_nonnegroots_f1,A_vals,...
    real_nonnegroots_f2,params,plot_pars,'vectorfield')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flag ‘vectorfield’ tells the function to evaluate the algebraic equations that are the right-hand side of the differential equations showing the value of time-derivatives at that point of the coordinate system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a parameter set with basal production rates falling within the bistable region of the bifurcation plot on Figure 2 for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n=4&lt;/script&gt; both variables have nullclines with 3 branches across the entire range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mbkoltai/mbkoltai.github.io/master/images/double_inhib_bistable_symm_vectorfield_n4.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:80%&quot; alt=&quot;n4_vectorfield&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4: Inhibition-coupled bistable genes, parameter set resulting in 4 stable fixed points.&lt;/strong&gt; Green and blue lines showing the stable branches of the nullclines, dash-dotted thinner lines the unstable ones. Vector field showing the derivatives of the two state variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stable branches are shown by thicker markers (green and blue) and the unstable ones by dashed-dotted thinner lines. The intersections of the stable branches have to be the fixed points of the system.&lt;br /&gt;
It is interesting to visualize this as well and also the basins of attractions of the fixed points. To do this we numerically integrate the ODEs from a grid of initial conditions and store the solutions in the cell &lt;em&gt;trajectories&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-MATLAB&quot;&gt;initvals=linspace(0,2.25,16); tspan=0:0.01:20; initvals_perms=permn(initvals,2);
options = odeset('RelTol',1e-4); % ,'AbsTol',at
trajectories=cell(1,size(initvals_perms,1));

for initv1=1:size(initvals_perms,1)
    disp(initv1/size(initvals_perms,1)); x0=initvals_perms(initv1,:);
    [t,x]=ode45(@(t,x)fcn_odes_double_inhib(t,x,params),tspan, x0);
    trajectories{initv1}=x;
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the parameter set above the trajectories look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/double_inhib_bistable_symm_manytrajs_n4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 5: Inhibition-coupled bistable genes: parameter set resulting in 4 stable fixed points.&lt;/strong&gt;  Trajectories from different initial conditions converging to one of the four fixed points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see how the unstable branches are the ‘frontiers’ of the basins of attraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting case is a parameter set when the nullcline don’t just intersect at given points, but overlap along a whole section:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/double_inhib_bistable_symm_trajs_n3_vectorfield.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 6: Inhibition-coupled bistable genes, parameter set resulting in overlapping nullclines yielding fixed points along the overlapping section.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case the overlapping section of the nullclines are all fixed points, so trajectories in the basin of attraction converge to different points of this line. This means (I think) there are infinitely many stable solutions that converge on the points of this line section in this region of the phase space. It would be interesting to explore what this means in terms of the polynomials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting question is what if we couple more than 2 bistable components. Would we get multistability with more than 4 fixed points? I might explore this question in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script with its functions are available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/multistable_coupled_toggle&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and they can be downloaded and used in MATLAB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gardner2000construction&quot;&gt;[1]T. S. Gardner, C. R. Cantor, and J. J. Collins, “Construction of a genetic toggle switch in Escherichia coli,” &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 403, no. 6767, p. 339, 2000. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;lu2013tristability&quot;&gt;[2]M. Lu, M. K. Jolly, R. Gomoto, B. Huang, J. Onuchic, and E. Ben-Jacob, “Tristability in cancer-associated microRNA-TF chimera toggle switch,” &lt;i&gt;The journal of physical chemistry B&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 117, no. 42, pp. 13164–13174, 2013. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!--- References  
[1] [Gardner, T.S., Cantor, C.R. and Collins, J.J., 2000. Construction of a genetic toggle switch in Escherichia coli. Nature, 403(6767), p.339.](https://www.nature.com/articles/35002131)  
[2] [Lu, M., Jolly, M.K., Gomoto, R., Huang, B., Onuchic, J. and Ben-Jacob, E., 2013. Tristability in cancer-associated microRNA-TF chimera toggle switch. The journal of physical chemistry B, 117(42), pp.13164-13174](https://www.researchgate.net/publication/236913602_Tristability_in_Cancer_Associated_miRNA-TF_Chimera_Toggle_Switch)
---&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="systems-biology" /><category term="nonlinear-dynamics" /><category term="multistability" /><category term="kinetics" /><category term="complex-systems" /><summary type="html">Fun with multistability (scripts+plots)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exact solving of stochastic continuous-time logical models</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/exastolog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exact solving of stochastic continuous-time logical models" /><published>2019-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/exastolog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/exastolog/">&lt;p&gt;I recently submitted a manuscript that presents a calculation method to calculate the stationary solution of stochastic, continuous-time logical (Boolean) models.&lt;br /&gt;
I adopted the mathematical technique from the field of chemical kinetics, specifically a number of articles from Jeremy Gunawardena and coauthors. These articles started with a small essay on the thresholding and switching properties of multisite (protein) phosphorylation &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/102/41/14617&quot;&gt;in PNAS&lt;/a&gt; back in 2005 and then with a beautiful paper in Nature on ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://vcp.med.harvard.edu/papers/multistability.pdf&quot;&gt;unlimited multistability&lt;/a&gt;’ in 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these articles the results were still somewhat &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt;, but they showed that the stationary solution of the kinetic equations describing post-translations modifications, which are nonlinear ordinary differential equations with bilinear terms complemented by some algebraic conservations, can be analytically obtained and that if we have multisite species there is no obvious limit to the number of stable steady states that these systems have.
Later on the results were generalized, culminating in the paper ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://vcp.med.harvard.edu/papers/jg-lap-dyn.pdf&quot;&gt;Laplacian dynamics on general graphs&lt;/a&gt;’ (2013) where they are most systematically summarized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fascinated by these papers during my PhD. When I started to work on stochastic Boolean models with continuous time, that we simulated with Monte Carlo simulations (same way as Gillespie algorithm is used for stochastic kinetics) it occurred to me only after some time that if we want to have the stationary solution only then this is in fact identical to the problem described by Gunawardena, so his method can be adopted for the state transition graph of a logical model.&lt;br /&gt;
The result from this work is now on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/794230v1&quot;&gt;biorXiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
I’ve also implemented the calculations as a MATLAB toolbox that can be downloaded and used with the help of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/exact-stoch-log-mod/tree/master/doc&quot;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="cancer" /><category term="systems-biology" /><category term="kinetics" /><category term="tools" /><summary type="html">By matrix method from kinetics</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dynamic behavior of sequentially determined values</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/seqvalues/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dynamic behavior of sequentially determined values" /><published>2019-03-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/seqvalues</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/seqvalues/">&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbkoltai.github.io/dynamic-prodprice-simplerepr/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; I discussed a simple model of sequentially defined prices of production. These production prices for any good are defined as the good’s input cost (wages + non-labour costs) plus a markup equal to the rate of profit/surplus labor in the entire (two department) economy.
As I discussed this model eventually converges to a stationary solution that is identical of the algebraic system of equations with identical input and output prices, ie.
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{p} = \mathbf{p}(\mathbf{A} + w \mathbf{l})(1+r)
\tag{1}\label{simul_val}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system of difference equations for (more than one) prices of production had a nonlinear term due to profit rate equalization, ie. redistribution of value produced in the different sectors:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{p}_{t+1} = \mathbf{p}_t (\mathbf{A} + w \mathbf{l})
(1 + \frac{ \mathbf{l} \mathbf{X} - \mathbf{p}_t w \mathbf{l} \mathbf{X} }{ \mathbf{p}_t (\mathbf{A} + w \mathbf{l}) \mathbf{X} } ) =
\mathbf{p}_t (\mathbf{A} + w \mathbf{l}) \frac{ ( \mathbf{p}_t \mathbf{A} + \mathbf{l}) \mathbf{X} }{ \mathbf{p}_t (\mathbf{A} + w \mathbf{l}) \mathbf{X} }
\tag{2}\label{unit_price_dynam_explicit}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that in the case of a model with only one good, so if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X&lt;/script&gt; are scalars, not matrices/vectors, the nonlinearity drops out and the system simplifies to
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_{t+1} = p_t a + l&lt;/script&gt;, that has an explicit solution, which is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_{t} = p_0 a^t + l \sum_{i=0}^{t-1} a^i = p_0 a^t  + \frac{l}{1-a} (1-a^t)&lt;/script&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
a&lt;1 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; (meaning there is a physical surplus) converges to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p^* = \frac{l}{1-a}&lt;/script&gt;. In this case there is no redistribution of added value through prices of production, so value and price are the same, equaling to the price of inputs plus the incorporated labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is more interesting to work with the more general case of multiple goods/sectors, but without the non-linearity, I will look at the dynamic behavior of values instead of prices of production, following an exchange between Duménil&amp;amp;Lévy (D&amp;amp;L) and P. Giussani around 2000 &lt;a href=&quot;#giussani&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#dumlevy&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I write the value of a particular good, I mean the value of its inputs plus the amount of (socially necessary) labour directly embodied in it, ie. using a sequential definition&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Lambda_t = \mathbf{A} \Lambda_{t-1} + \mathbf{L}_t
\tag{3}\label{dynamic_values}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or in the simultaneous description (dropping time subscripts):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Lambda = \mathbf{A} \Lambda + \mathbf{L}
\tag{4}\label{simult_values}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where again &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L&lt;/script&gt; is the column vector of labour values, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt; the input-output matrix, and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Lambda&lt;/script&gt; the column vector of unit values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solutions for the unit values are then for simultaneous values:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Lambda = (\mathbf{I} - \mathbf{A})^{-1} \mathbf{L}
\tag{5}\label{simult_values_sol}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and sequentially determined values:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Lambda_t = \mathbf{A}^{t} \Lambda_0 + (\mathbf{I} - \mathbf{A})^{-1} (\mathbf{I} - \mathbf{A}^{t} ) \mathbf{L}
\tag{6}\label{dynamic_values_sol}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is assumed (elements of) &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
A&lt;1 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; (otherwise we would have shrinking reproduction), therefore &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lim\limits_{t \to \infty}\Lambda_t = \Lambda^{* } = (I-A)^{-1} L&lt;/script&gt;, same as the simultaneous equation \ref{simult_values_sol}.
For this reason it was argued by Stamatis &lt;a href=&quot;#stamatisremarks&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#stamatiscategories&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; that the sequential formalism is simply an iterative calculation procedure to solve the algebraic equation of  \ref{simult_values_sol}, and not a model of economic dynamics. I will address this question later, first I will explore some dynamic properties of this formalism, independent of its interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was pointed out by D&amp;amp;L that in the sequential formalism it is possible to have growing labour productivity (falling labour inputs per unit of goods) with &lt;em&gt;growing&lt;/em&gt; unit values.
Specifically, if instead of a constant &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L&lt;/script&gt;, it is now a function of time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L_t = \alpha + \beta \gamma^t&lt;/script&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
0&lt;\gamma&lt;1 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;, that is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L&lt;/script&gt; will be monotonically decreasing with time, falling to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; eventually (the coefficients are column vectors).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The explicit solution for sequential values is then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Lambda_t =
A^t \Lambda_0 + (I - A)^{-1} (I-A^t) \mathbf{\alpha} + (A - \gamma I)^{-1} (A^t - \gamma^t I) \mathbf{\beta}
\tag{7}\label{dynamic_values_sol_L_t}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt; is a scalar, otherwise the last term is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
(A^t - \left&lt; \gamma^t \right&gt; I ) \beta %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;, with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt; \gamma \right&gt; %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; being the diagonal matrix from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt;.
Since the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A^t&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma^t&lt;/script&gt; terms are shrinking to zero with time, the equilibrium solution is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Lambda^{* } = (I-A)^{-1} \mathbf{\alpha}&lt;/script&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;again the same as in the simultaneous description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;L point out that if the initial value &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\Lambda_0 &lt; \Lambda^{* } %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;, then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Lambda^{t}&lt;/script&gt; will rise, converging to the equilibrium from below, even though the labour content is falling. D&amp;amp;L refer to this as a ‘productivity paradox’.
In fact, the behavior of sequential values is even more complex.
In equation \ref{dynamic_values_sol_L_t} there are exponential terms both in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt; suggesting the behavior can be non-monotonic. This is in fact what happens with certain parameter sets as shown by the numerical examples below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parameter set used was: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\mathbf{\alpha}= [0.2; 0.4], \mathbf{\beta}= [0.3; 0.1],
\mathbf{\gamma}= [0.9; 0.8],
\mathbf{A} = \begin{bmatrix} 2/3 &amp; 1/3 \\ 1/6 &amp; 1/2 \\ \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/unitprices_nonmonot_paradox.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1: Non-monotonic dynamics of sequential values with increasing productivity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This non-trivial and somewhat puzzling feature comes about because of two dynamical terms that can be seen in  equation \ref{dynamic_values_sol_L_t}: one coming from the input values of the previous period and the other from labor productivity.
If the initial input values are far from the stationary value (of the &lt;em&gt;simultaneous equations&lt;/em&gt; with that level of productivity) then it can take several iterations until the falling labor content becomes the dominant term, and this can result in non-monotonic behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the one-good case, it is easier to see the conditions for this. In this case the difference &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\epsilon&lt;/script&gt; between any two consecutive steps is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\epsilon = \left(\lambda_0 - \frac{\alpha}{1-a} + \frac{\beta}{a-\gamma} \right) a^t \left(1-\frac{1}{a} \right) +
\left(- \frac{\beta}{a - \gamma} \right) \gamma^t \left(1-\frac{1}{\gamma} \right)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denoting the difference between the initial and stationary value &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta = \lambda_0 - \frac{\alpha}{1-a}&lt;/script&gt;, and after some rearrangements, the condition for non-monotonic behavior is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\Delta &lt; \frac{\beta}{a-\gamma} \left( \frac{\gamma}{a}^{t-1} \frac{\gamma-1}{a-1} -1 \right) %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;, if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta &gt;0&lt;/script&gt; (increasing unit values for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda_0 &gt; \lambda^*&lt;/script&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta &gt; \frac{\beta}{a-\gamma} \left( \frac{\gamma}{a}^{t-1} \frac{\gamma-1}{a-1} -1 \right)&lt;/script&gt;, if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\Delta &lt; 0 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; (decreasing unit values for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\lambda_0 &lt; \lambda^* %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the numerical example above shows this can be satisfied in both cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this behavior of sequential values «paradoxical»?
No matter how we answer this question, it certainly would be an exaggeration to claim that what we see here is - even an extremely simplified - model of economic dynamics.
The technical coefficients of the system are defined independently from values, there are no feedback effects, and yet the system shows relatively complicated dynamic behavior already, depending on its initial value. This is not due to endogenous technical change or of disequilibrium between supply and demand, but simply to the dependence on the previous state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet this can also be seen as an interesting feature of the sequential model, in contrast to the simultaneous one, namely that the periods are connected: the output price/value of one period is the input of the next. This suggests that it can be used in a dynamical model of the circuit(s) of capital &lt;a href=&quot;#foley1982realization&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;.
If we have only one circuit per sector like above, this assumes that all capitals in that sector are synchronized, which is clearly not the case in reality.
But if they are not synchronized, the formalism would have to be more complex. When one circuit of capital is in the phase of production others are releasing new products to the market, which can devalue the inputs.
Therefore the value of inputs would not equal their original value, but would be - intuitively - some weighted average of past values of the inputs used by the individual circuits.
In my next posts I want to address this question of connecting a model of the circuit of capital with these different methods of value calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;giussani&quot;&gt;[1]P. Giussani, “Dynamic and Static Marxian Values,” &lt;i&gt;Political Economy&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 3, no. 3, pp. 5–19, 1998. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;dumlevy&quot;&gt;[2]G. Dumenil and D. Levy, “The Conservation of Value. A Rejoinder to Alan Freeman,” &lt;i&gt;Review of Radical Political Economics&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 32, no. 1, pp. 119–146, 2000. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;stamatisremarks&quot;&gt;[3]G. Stamatis, “Some remarks upon the article of Alan Freeman ’Marx without equilibrium,’” &lt;i&gt;Political Economy&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 3, no. 3, pp. 21–23, 1998. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;stamatiscategories&quot;&gt;[4]G. Stamatis, “The so-called Temporal Single System (TSS) the so-called Standard Simultaneous Methodology (SSM) and the correct definition of labour values,” &lt;i&gt;Political Economy&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 3, no. 5, pp. 23–44, 1999. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;foley1982realization&quot;&gt;[5]D. K. Foley, “Realization and Accumulation in a Marxian Model of the Circuit of Capital,” &lt;i&gt;Journal of Economic Theory&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 28, no. 2, pp. 300–319, 1982. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="political-economy" /><category term="economic-models" /><category term="classical-political-economy" /><category term="marxian-economics" /><category term="transformation-problem" /><summary type="html">Weird properties of dynamic labor values</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A toy model of dynamic prices of production</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dynamic-prodprice-simplerepr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A toy model of dynamic prices of production" /><published>2019-01-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dynamic-prodprice-simplerepr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dynamic-prodprice-simplerepr/">&lt;p&gt;I have not posted lately on A. Trigg’s book on reproduction schemas as I got into reading on the (in)famous ‘transformation problem’ and could not resist playing with some models in the literature. In one sentence the transformation problem is about whether the claim that the value of commodities is indirectly or directly determined by the average labour time needed for their production (+ non-labour inputs) is compatible with the observation/expectation that profit rates across sectors with different labour/capital ratios would tend toward equalization. I will not discuss this problem per se in this post, there is a lot of literature available on that, although this model can be regarded as a solution to the ‘transformation problem’.
I want to write down the equations of a dynamical model proposed in Kliman [1988] with numerical examples (but without the equations explicitly), of prices of production where the aggregate equalities (total price) = (total value) and (total surplus value) = (total profit) are satisfied, total supply can be sold in each period of production, and the balancing condition (see Eq. \eqref{balancing_cond}) between the two sectors of the economy is also met.
The model has the following assumptions and properties:&lt;br /&gt;
1) value is expressed in money, there is only one accounting system&lt;br /&gt;
2) non-labor inputs transfer their value to the products they are used up for, but no more or less&lt;br /&gt;
3) a given amount of labor adds the same amount of value, profit can therefore originate only from unpaid (surplus) labour: less is paid for wages than the amount of new value added by labour, the difference between the two appears as profit (for the entire economy, not for an individual sector)&lt;br /&gt;
4) the system shows &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbkoltai.github.io/reprod_multipl2/&quot;&gt;simple reproduction&lt;/a&gt; only: it is producing the same physical amounts of goods in each period, and the physical surplus (output minus inputs used up) takes the form of consumption goods only and it is consumed in each period instead of being redirected (accumulated) into the system as new capital goods or new consumption goods for an expanding workforce. The amount of non-labour inputs (constant capital) and work performed do not change.&lt;br /&gt;
5) the real wage is kept constant: the wage paid for workers enables them to buy the same amounts of consumption goods. The nominal wage can however change if the unit price of consumption goods change.&lt;br /&gt;
6) Profit rates are equalized&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course assumptions no. 2-3 can be (are) contested, and the idea that human labour is the only source of new value and therefore of profit can be rejected, but this - ie. the validity of the labour theory of value - is a topic for another post. Assumption no. &lt;em&gt;4-5&lt;/em&gt; are just convenient first assumptions, but the system can be changed to expanded reproduction etc. by altering its coefficients.
Assumption &lt;em&gt;6&lt;/em&gt; is reasonable as a tendency (capital flows in search of (sectors with) higher rates of return) but one should also have a mechanism implemented in a more serious model.
My goal here is just to build a small mathematical model that is internally consistent and has a dynamics that can later be made more realistic by introducing more detail. As the system is dynamic  prices and profit rates can change, which is a precondition to incorporate crises in the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like in the input-output models I &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbkoltai.github.io/reprod_multipl2/&quot;&gt;discussed previously&lt;/a&gt; we have two economic sectors (or departments), the first (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;) producing capital goods (this could be raw materials as well, any non-labour inputs used up in production), the second (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;) consumption goods (&lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;). Since we are dealing with simple reproduction and we will also abstract from fixed capital, therefore all capital goods are used up in each period of production, the total use of capital goods has to equal the total output (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1&lt;/script&gt;) of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;.
This gives us the equality
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1 = C_1 + V_1 + S_1 = C_1 + C_2&lt;/script&gt;, or,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_2 = V_1 + S_1
\tag{1}\label{balancing_cond}&lt;/script&gt;
In other words, the exchanges between the two departments (wages + profits in &lt;em&gt;D1&lt;/em&gt; = value of constant capital used up in &lt;em&gt;D2&lt;/em&gt;) have to be equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one important respect the current model will be different from the one discussed in the case of input-output tables and this will change the meaning of the equality of Equation \eqref{balancing_cond}. In the input-output description it is assumed (this assumption can be called ‘simultaneous valuation’) that unit prices for the two goods have to be the same when they enter as inputs and when they emerge as outputs in a given period of production.
Since unit prices cannot change what the system describes are the relative prices required to solve the system of algebraic equations that describe the input-output equalities. A uniform profit rate is normally assumed, which gives one more constraint for the price system, but since there is one more unknown than the number of equations, only relative prices can be calculated.
The input-output model as usually understood is then a model of equilibrium prices for given technical (input-output) coefficients and a level of real wage (units of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; paid for a unit of labour performed). In fact, because of the fact that input and output prices are the same and that profit rates are equal across sectors, both prices and the rate of profit are determined by the technical coefficients and the real wage rate (which is also a physical quantity), and in a sense prices become irrelevant (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/095382599107165&quot;&gt;Kliman (1999)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;
In contrast, in the model I will discuss here this assumption of the equality of input and output unit prices is dropped: input prices determine output prices sequentially. Consequently, instead of a system of algebraic equations with the same unit prices on both the right and left side, we will have a system of difference equations, that we need to provide with initial values in the first period of reproduction. In periods &lt;em&gt;t&amp;gt;1&lt;/em&gt; the input prices are given by the output prices of the preceding period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarise, in the simultaneous description we have unit prices as:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{p} = \mathbf{p}(\mathbf{A} + w \mathbf{l})(1+r)
\tag{2}\label{simul_val}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{p}&lt;/script&gt; is the row vector of unit prices, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{A}&lt;/script&gt; the input-output matrix, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w&lt;/script&gt; is the wage rate, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{l}&lt;/script&gt; is the row vector of labour inputs (quantities) per unit of output of each commodity and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; is the profit rate. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{A}&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l&lt;/script&gt; are given, whereas &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{p}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; are the unknowns.
Defining the ‘augmented’ input matrix &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{M} = A + w l&lt;/script&gt;, we can write the profit rate &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r = (pX - pMX)/pMX&lt;/script&gt;, where X is the column vector of gross outputs (physical quantities), but this is not an independent equation but rather comes from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{p X} = (\mathbf{p} \mathbf{M} (1+r))\mathbf{X}&lt;/script&gt;, so although &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r&lt;/script&gt; can be calculated (given &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{M}&lt;/script&gt;), but for production prices &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{p}&lt;/script&gt; we will only have the relative prices, as any set of absolute prices with the same ratios will satisfy the equations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the dynamic description we have instead:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{p}_{t+1} = \mathbf{p}_t(\mathbf{A} + w \mathbf{l})(1+r)
\tag{3}\label{dynamic unit prices}&lt;/script&gt;
which is a system of difference equations, not algebraic ones. Here, the input unit prices are a given, they are data, and they are mapped onto the output prices by the technical coefficients, the wage rate and the markup of the aggregate profit rate. Moreover, because of the third assumption above, the profit rate can now be independently determined from the input unit prices, technical coefficients, the wage rate and the amount of labour performed:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_{t,t+1} = (\mathbf{l}\mathbf{X} - \mathbf{p}_t w \mathbf{l} \mathbf{X})/
(\mathbf{p}_t (\mathbf{A} + w \mathbf{l}) \mathbf{X})
\tag{4}\label{profit_rate_dynamic}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Profit is the total amount of new value added minus the real wage of workers (quantity of consumption goods times their input unit price).
The rate of profit is given by dividing the amount of profit by total input costs that are also defined by technical coefficients, the wage rate and the input prices. It can be seen that the calculation of the profit rate only involves the input data of input prices and the coefficients, therefore it comes first. The calculation of unit output prices follows after, since they are the function of both the profit rate and input prices as can be seen from Equation \eqref{dynamic unit prices}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let us go back to the equality of simple reproduction in Equation \eqref{balancing_cond}:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_2 = V_1 + S_1&lt;/script&gt; (coming from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1 = C_1 + C_2&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt; being gross output of a sector)&lt;br /&gt;
In the equilibrium description of input-output tables, where input and output unit prices are equal, this equality is a relation between the inputs and outputs of the same period. As this is a description of equilibrium for a given set of technical and wage coefficients, there is in fact only one period, if we take another set of coefficients then we need to calculate another set of equilibrium prices.
But in the dynamic description this balancing condition is across two periods: the output of one period is the input of the next. In price terms, the output of capital goods has to equal the input of capital goods in the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; period. In physical terms, since it is simple reproduction, it is also true that the inputs (of one good) used up in the current period has to equal the output (of the same good) of the current period. But in terms of money the current period’s output is the input of the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; one, and it does not need to equal the input of this period, &lt;em&gt;unless&lt;/em&gt; the difference equations for unit prices have reached their stationary value. So the equality in the dynamic setting will be:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1(t) = C_1(t+1) + C_2(t+1)&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us write the dynamic equations for the unit prices in a form that they contain no other time-dependent variables, but only constants. All other variables of the system are governed by the unit prices as follows (from now on I put the time index in parenthesis instead of a subscript, as I use subscripts for department indices):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;constant capital: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_1(t) = \alpha X_1 p_1(t)&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_2(t) = (1-\alpha) X_1 p_1(t)&lt;/script&gt;, since the total physical amount and sectoral distribution of capital goods do not change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;wages: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1(t) = \beta_1 X_2 p_2(t)&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_2(t) = \beta_2 X_2 p_2(t)&lt;/script&gt;, since the real wage is defined as a fixed amount (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta_1&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta_2&lt;/script&gt;) of consumption goods (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_2&lt;/script&gt;) that the wages can buy, and distribution of the workforce does not change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;revenue: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m(t)=\mu X_2 p_2(t)&lt;/script&gt;, profit spent on consumption goods by capitalists, also kept constant in physical terms (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu X_2&lt;/script&gt;, and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu + \beta_1 + \beta_2 = 1&lt;/script&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;total (gross) output: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i(t) = p_i(t) X_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cost: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;K_1(t) = C_1(t) + V_1(t) = \alpha X_1 p_1(t) + \beta_1 X_2 p_2(t)&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;K_2(t) = (1-\alpha) X_1 p_1(t) + \beta_2 X_2 p_2(t)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;profit rate: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r(t) = \frac{L_T - (V_1(t)+V_2(t)) }{ K_1(t) + K_2(T)} = \frac{L_T - (\beta_1 + \beta_2) X_2 p_2(t)}{ p_1(t) X_1 + (\beta_1 + \beta_2) X_2 p_2(t) }&lt;/script&gt; (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L_T&lt;/script&gt; is total labour performed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the output price of the current period is the input of the next period, and gross output is equal to input costs and a markup equal to the aggregate profit rate, we have:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_i(t+1) X_i = W_i(t) = (C_i(t) + V_i(t)) (1 + r(t))
\tag{5}\label{unit_price_dynam_implicit}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dividing by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_i&lt;/script&gt; and substituting the expressions listed above we have:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{bmatrix} p_1(t+1) \\ p_2(t+1 )\\ \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} \alpha &amp; \beta_1 X_2 / X_1\\ (1 - \alpha) X_1 / X_2 &amp; \beta_2 \\ \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} p_1(t) \\ p_2(t)\\ \end{bmatrix} \frac{ p_1(t) + L_T/X_1 }{ p_1(t) + (\beta_1 + \beta_2) X_2/X_1 p_2(t) }
\tag{6}\label{unit_price_dynam_explicit} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a system of first-order, non-linear, autonomous difference equations, that - I think - cannot be solved analytically (so that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p(t)&lt;/script&gt; would be a function of time and parameters only), but it is easy to simulate numerically, or solve for its fixed point (in which case it becomes a quadratic equation, with one positive solution).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I simulated the system in MATLAB with the following numerical values (also used in the article cited below as a reference): &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L_T = 300&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha = 1/2&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta_1 = 1/6&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta_2 = 1/3&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu = 1/2&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_1 = 200&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_2 = 300&lt;/script&gt; and the initial values &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_1(0)=p_2(0)=1&lt;/script&gt;.
This is the plot of the dynamics of unit prices and some of the ratios of the system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/unitprices_ratios.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system satisfies the following equalities (these are all in price terms):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1(t) = C_1(t+1) + C_2(t+1) = p_1(t+1) X_1&lt;/script&gt;, output of capital goods of the current period equals input of capital goods in next period&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_1(t) + V_1(t) = C_2(t)&lt;/script&gt;, exchanges between the sectors have to balance (capitalist consumption + wage outlays from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; equals outlays on capital goods from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;, with the other transactions being within the two departments)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_2(t) = V_1(t+1) + V_2(t+1) + m(t+1) = p_2(t+1) X_2&lt;/script&gt;, output of consumption goods in current period equals outlay on wages plus consumption from profit (revenue) in next period&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum m_i(t) = \sum W_i(t-1) - \sum K_i(t)&lt;/script&gt;, total revenue, ie. profit that can be spent on consumption equals the difference between the output of the previous period minus outlays on wages and capital goods in the current period&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since unit prices are changing until we reach the stationary state, the amount of money needed for total outlays (wages + capital goods) is also changing (see on the plot above the ratio of costs), and since inputs (in this model) transfer their prices to the output, gross output in terms of price is also changing, though net value added does not. Once we reach the fixed point unit prices do not change anymore, therefore wages, profit, outlays on capital goods and gross output have also reached a stationary state. This final state is identical to the equilibrium price (equal input and output prices) solution to the system. The fixed point is obviously attracting, so sampling in initial values (for unit prices) will lead to the same stationary values, as shown in the plot below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/prices_prod_initval_sampling.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the dynamical system converges to this stationary state only because the technical coefficients, the physical productivity and relative sizes of the departments do not change in this model.
If the parameters change before the system converges to the fixed point, then the pre-equilibrium behavior will continue (see Giussani 1991).
This simple model satisfies the requirements of a labour theory of value that total profit equals total surplus (unpaid) labour, total price equals total value, and the sectoral balances of simple reproduction are also respected, although this is enforced by the assumptions of the model that I’ll mention below. The unit prices of the two goods are different from their values, so it is only through aggregate quantities that prices are determined by labour values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to add additional detail to the model, the first thing to add should probably be growing labour productivity that would also mean expanded reproduction, so that some of the surplus is recycled to the system and not consumed. The other component to add for a bit more realistic model is fixed capital. If we add these, then it can start to make sense to ask questions on how productivity growth will affect profitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several potential problems with this model. First is how can we know the amount of value a unit of labour adds or represents, and the assumption that this amount (the ‘monetary expression of labour time’) does not change.
The second is that non-labour inputs (there is only one type in this model, ‘capital goods’ in general) transfer the value that they were bought at, but what happens if due to changes in productivity the inputs are worth less when the production period comes to its end, than at their time of purchase, what amount of value would they transfer?
Third, nominal wages automatically adjust to the new price of wage goods, as wages are defined as a fixed physical amount of wage goods times the output price of the previous period, assuming perfect adjustment of wages to match the supply of wage goods.
Finally, since the price of total output is growing, there needs to be more money in the system then in the first round (with the coefficients and the initial values used above), so the money supply would have to expand. I will return to these problems in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;script&quot;&gt;Script&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mbkoltai/mbkoltai.github.io/blob/master/images/sequential_prices.m&quot;&gt;MATLAB script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/40470553&quot;&gt;Giussani: The Determination of Prices of Production, International Journal of Political Economy, Volume 21, 1991&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/030981688803500106&quot;&gt;Kliman, McGlone: The transformation non-problem and the non-transformation problem, Capital &amp;amp; Class, Vol 12, Issue 2, 1988&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/095382599107165&quot;&gt;Kliman, McGlone: A Temporal Single-system Interpretation of Marx’s Value Theory, Review of Political Economy, Volume 11, Number 1, 1999&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="political-economy" /><category term="economic-models" /><category term="classical-political-economy" /><category term="marxian-economics" /><category term="transformation-problem" /><category term="nonlinear-dynamics" /><summary type="html">With labor values and equilibrium</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The monetary circuit (I)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/monetary_circuit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The monetary circuit (I)" /><published>2018-11-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-11-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/monetary_circuit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/monetary_circuit/">&lt;!---&quot;*Central to this approach is an  application  of  the  Kalecki  principle,  that capitalists  earn  what  they
spend; the question being how an injection of money can circulate around the economy and return back to the capitalists.*&quot;
(Trigg)---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbkoltai.github.io/reprodkalecki/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; I discussed the so-called ‘Kalecki’ principle, which, in my understanding, is an equality between gross profits on the one side and spending on capital goods and capitalist consumption on the other, summarized in the phrase ‘&lt;em&gt;capitalists earn what they spend&lt;/em&gt;’. This statement implies a causal relationship, which - it seems to me - is not demonstrated by these algebraic relationship. To show that this spending &lt;em&gt;creates&lt;/em&gt; (enables/leads to) these profits, one needs a sequential (dynamic) description of how the initial amount spent circulates through the economic system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A framework to do this is the so-called monetary circuit. The theory of the monetary circuit was developed by A. Graziani and others and shows how an initial injection of money circulates through the economy and return back to the owners of businesses and how much money is needed to close the circuit completely, with all output sold. In the model by Graziani there is a distinction between workers, capitalists and banks. Banks give credit to firms, so they can finance their outlays on wages, since this step has to precede production and sale. Money in this model is credit money, that has symbolic value, but no intrinsic value, ie. it is not a commodity.
The starting point of the circuit is banks giving credit to firms to hire workers, who then produce commodities. Assuming that workers don’t save, wages are spent on consumer goods (&lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;), returning the money to firms. As the last step of the circuit, firms can then repay their debts, destroying the credit money they originally borrowed and the circuit is closed.&lt;br /&gt;
So the circuit is simply: banks –&amp;gt; firms –&amp;gt; workers –&amp;gt; firms –&amp;gt; banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this description it is only wages that have to be advanced by companies, as it does not concern itself with the purchase of capital goods, that is considered to be internal to firms. For this reason I find this description too restrictive and almost tautological. For me, the main problem is to show how the entire output can be ‘realized’ (purchased by money), even if there is an increment of the capital stock and/or the labour force (extended reproduction) and not all surplus takes the form of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; (consumption goods) that are consumed by owners at the end of the period of production.
Starting from a two-sector model and output grouped into gross wages and gross profit we can draw up the following table:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Departments&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Wages (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt;*)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Profits (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_i&lt;/script&gt;*)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Output &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; (&lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1&lt;/script&gt;*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_1&lt;/script&gt;*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;  (&lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_2&lt;/script&gt;*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_2&lt;/script&gt;*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 1: Two sectors, gross profit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we subsume capitalist consumption under wages (and there is no government sector or foreign trade), then the surplus of the &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; sector (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_2&lt;/script&gt;) matches the wage bill of the capital goods sector, ie.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_2^* = V_1^*
\tag{1}\label{p2_equals_v1}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If in this model only wages are advanced, then the sum of advanced money equals the output of the &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; sector:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M = V_1^* + V_2^* = P_2^* + V_2^* = W_2
\tag{2}\label{advanced_wages}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in this case it would seem there is not enough money to buy up the entire output, the capital goods sector does not have the funds to reimburse the banks and the circuit cannot be closed.
A simple answer to this is a ‘single swap’ approach (&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/cje/article-abstract/28/2/173/1681265&quot;&gt;Nell, 2004&lt;/a&gt;), that a larger sum &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M=W_1+W_2&lt;/script&gt; is advanced, so that all output can be bought up in a single monetary circuit. But this makes things too easy, resulting in the buildup of extra funds in the capital goods sector when it receives revenue from the consumer goods sector equal to its wage bill, but it also borrowed that amount from banks. Putting aside this too general assumption, &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/cje/article-abstract/28/2/173/1681265&quot;&gt;EJ Nell (2004)&lt;/a&gt; worked out one solution based on multiplier effects within departments, that I discuss next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nell’s solution: realizing the total output through multiplier effects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘single swap’ solution just mentioned leaves no place for transactions taking place sequentially, with a given amount of money that is smaller than &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M&lt;/script&gt;, circulating between households (workers and capitalists as consumers) and firms in the two sectors.
The ‘mutual exchange’ between sectors is key, as firms earn income by selling outputs to firms in the other (and in the same) sector.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/cje/article-abstract/28/2/173/1681265&quot;&gt;EJ Nell (2004)&lt;/a&gt;’s solution based on mutual exchanges starts with the following assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Production is defined in distinct periods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In each period of production all capital goods are completely used up (100% depreciation).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consumption and capital goods are both carried forward from the previous period, so that at the start of the period, there are inventories of capital and consumption goods ‘inherited’ from the previous period&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Production in the current period is to replace items (&lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt;) used up by firms and consumers in the current period&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The starting point in this model is the advance of wages in the capital goods sector (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;), but it could be the consumer goods sector too, the point is just to initiate the process. This injection of money then circulates through the system in a sequence of stages, ‘realizing’ (enabling the purchase of) the output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 1&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; borrows money from banks, pays wage bill to workers of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;. Workers spend this money to purchase consumption goods from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 2&lt;/strong&gt;: After selling consumption goods to workers of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; pays wages to its own workers, who spend it on &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;, so that the money returns back to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;, to be spent on capital goods from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 3&lt;/strong&gt;: From the sales of &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; firms can advance wages and purchase their own capital goods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schematically, the sequence is:&lt;br /&gt;
banks -(0)-&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; -(1)-&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; workers -(2)-&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; -(3)-&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; workers -(4)-&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; -(5)-&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; -(6)-&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; workers
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tag{3}\label{v1_sequence}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can see a &lt;em&gt;causal&lt;/em&gt; multiplier effect, as the initial injection of money as advanced wages by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1&lt;/script&gt;, leads to the realization of commodities of a (multiple times) higher total value.
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1&lt;/script&gt; &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; is sold in step (2), then again &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_2&lt;/script&gt; of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; in step (4), and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_1&lt;/script&gt; (?) of &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; sold in step (5), and more &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; in step (6) when firms in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; buy &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; from firms within their sector.
The flow of money can be seen on this figure I created:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/v1_moneyflow_circuit.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1: the flow of money through both departments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The red arrows are transactions where a part of the output is ‘realized’ (purchased).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total money output is:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_T = V_1^* + V_2^* + P_1^* + P_2^* = 2 V_1^* + V_2^* + P_1^*
\tag{4}\label{total_money_output}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.fr/books?id=T_Q8D-ewMkEC&quot;&gt;Nell (1998)&lt;/a&gt; describes a multiplier relationship of the wages paid out in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; on the wages of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;: in the first round this effect is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1^*&lt;/script&gt;, then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w n_2 V1^*&lt;/script&gt;, then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(w n_2)^2 V1^*&lt;/script&gt;, with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n_2&lt;/script&gt; being the labour coefficient (share of labour in total output) and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w&lt;/script&gt; the wage rate, so that, as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
w n_2 &lt; 1 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_2^* = V_1^* \sum_{i=0}^\infty (w n_2)^i = \frac{1}{1 - w n_2} V_1^*
\tag{5}\label{v1_v2_multiplier}&lt;/script&gt;
One thing not clear to me is why one would say that in the first round &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; pays out &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1^*&lt;/script&gt; as wages, and only from the second &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w n_2 V_1^*&lt;/script&gt;, and in later cycles &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; always &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(w n_2)^i V_1^*&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nell also assumes two subsectors in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; (capital goods sector), the first selling &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;, the second to other firms in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;, let us call these &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1,2}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1,1}&lt;/script&gt; (and assume equal labour coefficients and wage rates).
A multiplier effect occurs in the exchanges between the subsectors and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;.
First, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1,2}&lt;/script&gt; sells &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;, receiving &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_2^* (=V_1^* )&lt;/script&gt;. It uses &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w n_1 P_2^*&lt;/script&gt; to pay back its loans (if this is not for wages, why the scaling with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w n_1&lt;/script&gt;?) and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1-w n_1)P_2^*&lt;/script&gt; to buy &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1,1}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1,1}&lt;/script&gt; spends &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1-w n_1)(1-w n_1)P_2^*&lt;/script&gt;. But if this is sales within &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1,1}&lt;/script&gt;, then the cycle would stop here, whereas Trigg (summarizing Nell) writes that there is a multiplier effect here again, with the sum:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P_1^* = P_2^* \sum_{i=0}^\infty (1 - w n_1)^i = \frac{1}{w n_1} P_2^*
\tag{6}\label{p1_p2_multiplier}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems to me, to have this multiplier effect, firms of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; should use their proceeds to pay back their loans only in the last cycle, before that the mutual exchanges within &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; need to repeat until convergence as in \eqref{p1_p2_multiplier}. In fact, we need to assume that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1,1}&lt;/script&gt; receives back its own capital expenditure &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1-w n_1)(1-w n_1)P_2^*&lt;/script&gt;, repeating this cycle until convergence and only then spending it, together with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w n_1 (1-w n_1) P_2^*&lt;/script&gt; on wages, so in total we have &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1-w n_1) P_2^*&lt;/script&gt; of wage outlays from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1,1}&lt;/script&gt;. I show the multiplier of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; in this model as I understand it on Figure 2 below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/D1_multiplier.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2: the multiplier of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the two ‘auto-loops’ (to borrow a term from systems biology) within the sectors that generate the multiplier effect. One is the circulating of wages within &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; through its workers: in each round &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; pays wages to its workers that they repay for the same amount of consumption goods. In each round the revenue returned is scaled by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w n_2&lt;/script&gt; when paid out as wages, which means that the total amount paid out as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_2^*&lt;/script&gt; wages (and total amount of consumption good sold within the sector) is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1^* \sum_{i=1}^\infty (w n_2)^i = \frac{w n_2}{1 - w n_2}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, within &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; there is first the payment from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1,2}&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1,1}&lt;/script&gt; of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1-w n_2) P_2^*&lt;/script&gt;, then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_{1-1}&lt;/script&gt; buys &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; from itself in a sequence, multiplying the initial amount with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(1-w n_2)&lt;/script&gt; in each step so in total &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1^* \sum_{i=1}^\infty (1 - w n_1)^i = \frac{1 - w n_1}{w n_1} = \frac{1}{w n_1} - 1&lt;/script&gt;. So to me it seems the multiplier expressions should be slightly different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we substitute the multiplier expressions as in Equation \eqref{v1_v2_multiplier} and \eqref{p1_p2_multiplier} into Equation \eqref{total_money_output} we get an overall multiplier relationship:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W_T = 2 V_1^* + \frac{1}{1-w n_2} V_1^* + \frac{1}{w n_1} V_1^* =
V_1^* \left(2 + \frac{1}{1-w n_2} + \frac{1}{w n_1} \right)
\tag{7}\label{total_money_output_multipl}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own calculation this should rather be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;W_T = V_1^* \left(2 + \frac{w n_2}{1-w n_2} + \left(\frac{1}{w n_1}-1 \right) \right) =
V_1^* \left(\frac{1}{1-w n_2} + \frac{1}{w n_1} \right)
\tag{8}\label{total_money_output_multipl_corr}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is the correct expression, because if we take equation \eqref{total_money_output_multipl}, and consider that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w n_i = V_i^* /(V_i^* + P_i^* )&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1^* = P_2^*&lt;/script&gt; then we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;2 V_1^* + V_2^* + P_1^* = 2 V_1^* + \frac{1}{1-w n_2} V_1^* + \frac{1}{w n_1} V_1^*&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V_2^* + P_1^* = \frac{1}{1 - V_2^* /(V_2^* + P_2^* ) } V_1^* + \frac{V_1^* + P_1^* }{V_1^* } V_1^*&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;V_2^* + P_1^* = \frac{V_2^* + P_2^* }{ P_2^* } V_1^* + V_1^* + P_1^*&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;0 = P_2^* + V_1^* ,&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which cannot be true. Therefore I think the formula in \eqref{total_money_output_multipl_corr} is the correct one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this model was to show that the initial outlay of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1^*&lt;/script&gt; &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; sufficient to fund a much larger total income (wages and profits) in both sectors. At last, we can see a chain of causation behind the algebraic relationship of a multiplier. The simple answer to how it is possible to realize the total output is by the circulation of money between and within sectors, including the circulation between firms and their workers. A substantially smaller monetary advance than the value of the total output circulates through the system multiple times, enabling the transactions through which the entire output can be sold.
To see how this happens exactly cries out for a dynamic model, probably using difference equations. (As a first approximation, we can just use a spreadsheet where rows stand for time points (stages) and columns the inventories of commodities and money held by the departments, workers and capitalists.)
To be able to realize the full output &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_T&lt;/script&gt; the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; transactions should occur only once, whereas for the two intra-department multiplier effects to converge these refluxes of money need to happen infinitely many times. Are these assumptions reasonable? This requirement could be relaxed by starting the circuit with a bigger initial outlay than &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1^*&lt;/script&gt;. A somewhat confusing aspect of this model is why &lt;em&gt;gross&lt;/em&gt; wages are paid as the initial outlay, not just &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1&lt;/script&gt;, as the expansion of the workforce by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV_1&lt;/script&gt; should happen only in the next period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that this model tries to answer is not identical with the ‘Marxian’ realization problem, although very similar to it. Here a production period starts with the two departments having inventories of &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; inherited from the previous period, but no money, and the question is whether all inventories can be sold, and if yes, what initial amount of money is required to do so. If inventories are sold, then production can take place and a supply of new commodities is produced, that will have to be realized in the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; period of production, where the same realization problem has to be solved. Notice that in this description production and specifically the production of surplus value is not explicitly addressed, or it is obscured in the gross profit category. Also, there is in fact many cycles of production and sale, but initially I wanted to have a model of a &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; cycle of production and sale that is closed (everything can be sold).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other way to look at the problem is to say that firms (and owners as consumers) have funds at the starting point, which they use to buy from the inventories of &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; (inherited from previous period) and (through wages) the inventories of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; that are available at the start of production. Production takes place and the supply of new products have a higher value (surplus value added by labor over paid wages) than the initially spent amount on wages and capital goods - how can it be bought up? In this second formulation, the concept of the production of surplus value is embedded.
It is this formulation of the problem that I turn in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/title/marxian-reproduction-schema-money-and-aggregate-demand-in-a-capitalist-economy/oclc/946076663&quot;&gt;Andrew Trigg, Marxian reproduction schema: money and aggregate demand in a capitalist economy. Routledge, 2009&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="political-economy" /><category term="economic-models" /><category term="marxian-economics" /><category term="demand" /><category term="monetary-circuit" /><summary type="html">Monetary realization of profits by a multiplier effect</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Expanded reproduction and the Kalecki principle</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reprodkalecki/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Expanded reproduction and the Kalecki principle" /><published>2018-10-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reprodkalecki</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reprodkalecki/">&lt;p&gt;In this post, following &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/title/marxian-reproduction-schema-money-and-aggregate-demand-in-a-capitalist-economy/oclc/946076663&quot;&gt;Trigg’s book&lt;/a&gt; on reproduction schemas, I will explore how the work of Michał Kalecki contributes to answering the question where the demand for the surplus part of total output comes from.
One can explore in more detail how surplus value is allocated by its use: some of it is used for expanding the capital stock (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dC_i&lt;/script&gt;), some for expanding the workforce &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV_i&lt;/script&gt;) and some for capitalist consumption (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i&lt;/script&gt;), the subscript &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; referring to departments.
Also, Department 2 can be disaggregated into two departments, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; producing consumption goods (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;CoG&lt;/script&gt;) for capitalists and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_3&lt;/script&gt; producing &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;CoG&lt;/script&gt; for workers.
Using the same table as in the previous post, with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; split into two and surplus value allocated by use, we have the table:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Departments&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Constant capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Variable capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Surplus value &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;~&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;~&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Total output &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dC_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;400&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;550&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;275&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;220&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;36 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{2}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;18 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1100&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_3&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;950&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;475&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;380&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;63 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;31 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{2}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1900&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1750&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;150&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 1: Three-sector (expanded) reproduction schema&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt; column is the amount of constant capital used up in the given period of production, in this case 5500. The columns that represent surplus value/product are different from the columns &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt;, because the former are the final outputs from this period of production, and they are not used as inputs in this period. Since there is accumulation (the capital stock is incremented), the output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1=6000&lt;/script&gt;) is more than the total input of &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_1=5500&lt;/script&gt;.
If however we add to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt; the additional units of constant capital (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dC_i&lt;/script&gt;), and do the same with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV_i&lt;/script&gt;, creating ‘&lt;em&gt;ex post&lt;/em&gt;’ variables &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;* and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt;*, then the row sums and columns match:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Departments&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;*&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt;*&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Capitalist consumption &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Total output &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4400&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;586 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{2}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;293 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;220&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_3&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1013 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;506 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{2}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;380&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1900&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 2: ‘ex post’ three-sector reproduction schema (quantities at the end of period)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The columns &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt; I would interpret as the inputs of &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; and labour (workforce/wages) in the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; period, respectively, whereas &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i&lt;/script&gt; is the part of the profit received in sector &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; that is spent on consumption by owners, instead of accumulation. So &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;* and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt; are mixed variables in the sense that some of it is the input in the current period and some the increment added in the current, but used in the next period.
We have the equalities of outputs by sector to outputs grouped by use:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1 = C_1&lt;/script&gt;* &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+ C_2&lt;/script&gt;* &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+ C_3&lt;/script&gt;* &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;= C_1 + dC_1 + C_2 + dC_2 + C_3 + dC_3&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_2 = u_1 + u_2 + u_3&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_3 = V_1&lt;/script&gt;* &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+ V_2&lt;/script&gt;* &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+ V_3&lt;/script&gt;* &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;= V_1 + dV_1 + V_2 + dV_2 + V_3 + dV_3&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tag{1}\label{outputs_use}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expressed in words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1&lt;/script&gt;, total output of &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; (means of production) = &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; needed for replacement and accumulation (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i + dC_i&lt;/script&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_2&lt;/script&gt;, total output of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; for capitalists = profit extracted by capitalists, spent on personal consumption.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_3&lt;/script&gt;, total output of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; for workers (replacement and new workforce)’ = total wage bill (of workers in &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; period, including newly hired workers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!--- It is the parts of the output used for accumulation, $$dC + dV$$ whose realization (source of demand) is not trivial. $$V$$ and $$C$$ are spent at the beginning of the period and the demand for $$u$$ comes from the private wealth of the owners (that they then receive as profits for their companies). If the entire surplus part is in the form of capitalist consumption $$u$$, then there is no demand problem: all the demand for $$u$$ comes from owners' private funds, which then they receive back as the profit of their companies in $$D_2$$. But how about expanded reproduction?   --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also have the sectoral equalities:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1 = (C_1 + dC_1) + (V_1 + dV_1) + u_1 \\
W_2 = (C_2 + dC_2) + (V_2 + dV_2) + u_2  \\
W_3 = (C_3 + dC_3) + (V_3 + dV_3) + u_3
\tag{2}\label{sectoral_outputs}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one more rearrangement (coming from Kalecki): defining gross profits &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_i&lt;/script&gt;* as total output minus &lt;em&gt;ex post&lt;/em&gt; variable capital, ie. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_i&lt;/script&gt;* &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;= W_i - V_i&lt;/script&gt;*. At this point it’s not yet clear how to interpret gross profits meaningfully. &lt;em&gt;Ex post&lt;/em&gt; variable capital will be spent in the next period of production from gross revenue, but this is also true for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;*. At any rate, if we reorder terms this way, adding &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;* to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u_i&lt;/script&gt;, we get the table with gross profits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Departments&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt;*&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_i&lt;/script&gt;*&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Total output &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;293 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;806 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{2}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_3&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;506 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{2}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1393 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{1}{3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1900&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 3: Kalecki’s interpretation of the three-sector schema (ex post variable capital and gross profits)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the same as grouping the terms in the output as:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i = (V_i + dV_i) + (C_i + dC_i + u_i)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An equality becomes visible from this table, namely that the surplus of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_3&lt;/script&gt; produces (surplus in the sense that it is in excess of the wage bill of its own workers) is equal to the wage bill of the other two sectors:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_3 = V_1&lt;/script&gt;* &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+ V_2&lt;/script&gt;*
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tag{3}\label{wage_goods_gross_profit}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we then add the gross profits of the other two sectors, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_1&lt;/script&gt;* and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_2&lt;/script&gt;*, we get:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_1 + P_2 + P_3 = V_1&lt;/script&gt;* &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+ P_1 + V_2&lt;/script&gt;* &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;+ P_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P = W_1 + W_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tag{4}\label{total_gross_profit_outputs_equal}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that total gross profit in the economy is equal to the (gross) output of the sector producing capital goods (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;) and capitalist &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;). Since gross profit is defined as all spending on capital goods (replacement + incremental) and capitalist consumption, and these are supplied by sectors 1 and 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trigg writes that Kalecki interpreted this ‘&lt;em&gt;ex post&lt;/em&gt; identity’ as following: ‘&lt;em&gt;[T]he money expenditures by capitalists upon consumption and investment that generate the resultant volume of profits&lt;/em&gt;’, or shortly ‘&lt;em&gt;capitalists earn what they spend&lt;/em&gt;’.
&lt;!---Again, on a first sight, to me this sounds like causation backwards in time, as those investments and consumption expenditures can only happen at the end of the current period or at the beginning of the next one, once the owners have already received these profits.--&gt;
It is easy to see that ‘capitalists earn what they spend’ is true in the case of simple reproduction where the personal consumption of owners provides the demand for the surplus product, and returns to them as profit, but it less clear for expanded reproduction. In expanded reproduction some of the surplus product takes the form of new constant capital and new workers, so the demand must come from advanced amounts of money by the ‘departments’ (companies) themselves, not capitalists as consumers. To clearly see how this is possible, I need to write explicitly the sequence of payments/sales and production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now I’ll go on with the derivation as in the book. The three-sector schema can be represented in an input-output table as below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; (inputs)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; (inputs)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_3&lt;/script&gt; (inputs)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dC&lt;/script&gt; (addit. constant)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV&lt;/script&gt; (addit. variable)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u&lt;/script&gt; (capit. consumption)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt; (total output)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; (outputs by use)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;550&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;950&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_3&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;275&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;475&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;150&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1900&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;275&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;475&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1750&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbkoltai.github.io/reprod_multipl2&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; (new/net) investment is classified here as final demand (it is not an input in this period of production), specifically as additional constant (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dC&lt;/script&gt;) and variable (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV&lt;/script&gt;) capital. Total personal consumption of capitalists is in column &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u&lt;/script&gt;, under &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equality of Equation \eqref{wage_goods_gross_profit} reads in terms of the I/O table as:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_3 = W_3-(V_3+dV_3)=(V_1+dV_1)+(V_2 + dV_2)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wage terms are &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i = X_{3i}&lt;/script&gt;, so then the equation is:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_3 - (X_{33} + dV_3) = (X_{31} + dV_1) + (X_{32} + dV_2)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
and since none of the output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; can take the form of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV&lt;/script&gt;, therefore &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV_1 = dV_2 = 0&lt;/script&gt;, then this simplifies to:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_3 - (X_{33} + dV_3) = X_{31} + X_{32}
\tag{5}\label{use_output_3}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, all the output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_3&lt;/script&gt; not used by itself for replacement and expansion of its workforce is, logically, used by the other two sectors.
Also, it is more clearly visible that&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S = u + dC + dV = u + I
\tag{6}\label{surplus_investm_capcons}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
ie. surplus value (total profit) = capitalist consumption + investment (accumulation).
This equation is not the same as \eqref{total_gross_profit_outputs_equal}, because there gross profit P* is defined as all spending on capital goods and capitalist consumption, whereas here it is only the part spent on accumulation (&lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; capital goods and labour) and capitalist consumption.
This is interpreted by Trigg/Kalecki as ‘&lt;em&gt;capitalists cast money into circulation as aggregate demand on capitalist consumption and investment, which is realized as surplus value&lt;/em&gt;’ (p. 35). (There is again a nagging question of causality here left unanswered.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be rendered as a ‘Kalecki multiplier’, by defining capitalist consumption &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u&lt;/script&gt; as made up of a constant part &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B_0&lt;/script&gt; and a part dependent on profits as a fraction &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; of total profits &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u = B_0 + \lambda P
\tag{7}\label{kalecki_u_lambda}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P&lt;/script&gt; is total profits. Since &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P = u + I&lt;/script&gt;,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P = B_0 + \lambda P + I
\tag{8}\label{eq8}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
and therefore
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P = \frac{B_0 + I}{1-\lambda}
\tag{9}\label{eq9}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equation \eqref{eq9} represents a ‘multiplier’ relationship between total profits and total ‘exogenous’ expenditure by capitalists (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B_0 + I&lt;/script&gt;: constant capitalist consumption + new investment), with a multiplier effect of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1/(1-\lambda)&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since profits consist of capitalist consumption and investment, the components of the final demand &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f&lt;/script&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://mbkoltai.github.io/reprod_multipl2/&quot;&gt;see previous post&lt;/a&gt;, Equations 5 and 13), this can be substituted into the macro-income (‘Keynesian’) multiplier &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y = \frac{1}{e}f&lt;/script&gt;, yielding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;y = \frac{1}{e (1-\lambda)} (B_0 + I)
\tag{10}\label{kalecki_multipl}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that the ‘Keynesian’ multiplier now has the terms &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt;, the share of surplus value, and the ‘Kalecki multiplier’ &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1/(1-\lambda)&lt;/script&gt;, with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda&lt;/script&gt; being the fraction of profits spent on consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once more, we have a macro-identity here, but the question of whether the necessary amount of money is there to sell all outputs (and if yes where does it come from) in the case of expanded reproduction still hangs over these identities. This question can be addressed in the framework of the monetary circuit, which I will discuss in my next post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/title/marxian-reproduction-schema-money-and-aggregate-demand-in-a-capitalist-economy/oclc/946076663&quot;&gt;Andrew Trigg, Marxian reproduction schema: money and aggregate demand in a capitalist economy. Routledge, 2009&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="political-economy" /><category term="economic-models" /><category term="classical-political-economy" /><category term="marxian-economics" /><category term="kalecki" /><category term="demand" /><summary type="html">Profits = investment + capitalist consumption?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The reproduction schema and the ‘Keynesian multiplier’ (II)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/reprod_multipl2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The reproduction schema and the 'Keynesian multiplier' (II)" /><published>2018-09-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/reprod_multipl2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/reprod_multipl2/">&lt;p&gt;In this post I follow up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbkoltai.github.io/reprod_multipl/&quot;&gt;the previous one&lt;/a&gt; where I discussed the idea of a ‘multiplier’ that relates net income to net investment in an economic system. Both there and here I  follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/title/marxian-reproduction-schema-money-and-aggregate-demand-in-a-capitalist-economy/oclc/946076663&quot;&gt;a book&lt;/a&gt; by Andrew Trigg.
The problem with the ‘Keynesian’ approach outlined in the previous post is that it analyzes the system only in terms of net income (wages and profit) and does not account for the capital stock that also has to be reproduced (and potentially expanded).&lt;br /&gt;
A framework wherein the reproduction of constant capital can be analyzed is the so-called reproduction schema. The reproduction schema, first consistently developed in (what we know as) Volume 2 of Capital by Karl Marx, describes how in a given period of production the total social capital including both ‘variable’ (human labour) and ‘constant’ (machines) capital can be reproduced and potentially expanded. Marx used numerical examples in his writings, but the schema can be analyzed in symbolic form with the help of input-output tables and the tools of linear algebra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below in &lt;em&gt;Table 1&lt;/em&gt; is a numerical example of &lt;em&gt;simple&lt;/em&gt; reproduction, meaning that the amount of constant capital does not change from one period of production to the other. All the surplus value (profit) that is produced (received for the surplus fraction of the output) is consumed by the owners of capital, and not reinvested (accumulated).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Departments&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Constant capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Variable capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Surplus value &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Total output &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;D1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;D2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 1: simple reproduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, department 1 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; produces means of production (&lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt;), whereas &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; produces consumption goods (&lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;).
Each is represented by a row, with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt; standing for the total output. I prefer to normalize this table by the total output of the economy (9000), to see quantities in fractional terms, getting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Departments&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Constant capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Variable capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Surplus value &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Total output &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4/9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2/3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2/9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2/3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 1: simple reproduction&lt;/em&gt; (normalized)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constant capital produced (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1=2/3&lt;/script&gt;) is equal to constant capital consumed (sum of the column &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;) in this period of production. The amount of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; produced &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_2 = V_1 + V_2 + S_1 + S_2 = 1/3&lt;/script&gt;, so all profits will be spent on buying consumer goods (throughout it is assumed there is no saving from wages either).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be unrealistic if it were meant as a model of a capitalist economy, since capitalism is about growth (accumulation), but it is useful analytically. For if there is expansion, simple reproduction is still embedded within the growing economic system, but now it adds new units to its capital stock and/or its workforce as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A model of a growing economy is what we call &lt;em&gt;expanded reproduction&lt;/em&gt;, a numerical example of which is in &lt;em&gt;Table 2&lt;/em&gt; below&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Departments&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Constant capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Variable capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Surplus value &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Total output &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;750&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;750&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1750&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1750&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 2: expanded reproduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us normalize again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Departments&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Constant capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Variable capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Surplus value &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Total output &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4/9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2/3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11/18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7/36&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7/36&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 2: expanded reproduction (normalized)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is now more constant capital produced (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_1 = 2/3 = 12/18&lt;/script&gt;) than consumed (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_1+C_2=11/18&lt;/script&gt;), ie. accumulation is now possible, 1/18 (~5.6%) more constant capital will be available in the next round of production.
Correspondingly, all income is now more than all consumption goods (&lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;) produced:
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;V_1 + V_2 + S_1 + S_2 = 7/18 &gt; W_2 = 6/18&lt;/script&gt;, as some of the profit, namely 1/18 will be directed to accumulation. It is not trivial how the incomes and the outputs (or supply and demand) match, and what is the temporal sequence. I’ll return to this later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The (to-be-)accumulated capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta W&lt;/script&gt; is
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Delta W = W_1 - (C_1+C_2) = V_1 + S_1 - C_2 = 1/18
\tag{1}\label{eq1}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ie. it is new value added (=net income) in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; minus the constant capital consumed in the &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; department &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
This matches the part of total net income (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/script&gt;) &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; spent on consumption, which is&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Y - W_2 = Y_1 + Y_2 - (Y_2 + C_2) = Y_1 - C_2 = V_1 + S_1 - C_2 = 1/18
\tag{2}\label{eq2}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to input-output analysis, we have a case here of two sub-systems (departments) using the other’s output as an input, while - if there is expansion - some of the output is not used as an input in the present period.
Consumption from profit (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; bought from profit) is one component of this final output and it is not redirected into the system as an input.
The addition to the capital stock (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dC&lt;/script&gt;) is not used as an input in the &lt;em&gt;present&lt;/em&gt; cycle, although it will be in the next. Finally, there can be an addition to the labour force (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV&lt;/script&gt;) too in the next period matched by unconsumed &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;.
This last category was not visible in &lt;em&gt;Table 2&lt;/em&gt;, as the &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; of the outputs was not detailed there. It shows that capitalists can spend some of their profit on &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;, but not for their own personal consumption (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u&lt;/script&gt;), but for expanding the labour force (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV&lt;/script&gt;). Either way (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dV&lt;/script&gt; or &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u&lt;/script&gt;), this will go into buying up the output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;. Since total surplus value will have to equal total final product, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_1 + S_2 = dC + dV + u&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can turn &lt;em&gt;Table 2&lt;/em&gt; into an input-output (I/O) table. If we read the I/O table row-wise, we have the output of one department, arranged into columns by the &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; of that part of the output. If we read down a column, we have all the inputs for a given department (or for a type of final product).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; (inputs)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; (inputs)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;dC (new C)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;dV (new V)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;u (capitalist consum.)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt; (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum&lt;/script&gt;)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; (outputs)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_{11}&lt;/script&gt;=4/9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_{12}&lt;/script&gt;=1/6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2/3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; (outputs)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/60&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11/90&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2/3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1/3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 3: I/O table of expanded reproduction from Table 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_{ij}&lt;/script&gt; stands for the amount of capital goods (&lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt;) produced by department &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; used as an input by department &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt;. The gross (physical) output of department &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; is denoted as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_j&lt;/script&gt;. We can then define input coefficients &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a_{ij} = X_{ij}/X_j&lt;/script&gt; as the ratio of the gross output of department &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; it builds into this output from department &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;. This is the same as saying that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a_{ij}&lt;/script&gt; is the input coming from department &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_i&lt;/script&gt; into one unit of output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_j&lt;/script&gt;. For instance &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a_{12} = X_{12}/X_2 = (1/6)/(1/3) = 1/2&lt;/script&gt;, of the output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; comes from the output (&lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt;) of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; used by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; as an input.
Consumer goods are not industrial inputs, so these input coefficients refer only to the output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt;. One could say that workers in both sectors use consumer goods (output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;) in the same way, but this is rather after (and/or outside) the production process than a part of it. At any rate I’ll use the notation in Trigg’s book to reproduce the derivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; instead of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a_{ij}&lt;/script&gt;, we have the product &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h_i l_j&lt;/script&gt;. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l_j&lt;/script&gt; is the labour coefficient &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l_j = L_j/X_j&lt;/script&gt;, where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L_j&lt;/script&gt; is the number of labour units employed in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_j&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_j&lt;/script&gt; (same as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_j&lt;/script&gt; before) the gross output.
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h_i&lt;/script&gt; (which is defined for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h_2&lt;/script&gt; only) is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h_i = B_i/L&lt;/script&gt;, or concretely &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h_2 = B_2/L&lt;/script&gt;, the ratio of total consumption of the 2nd physical good (ie. &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;) to the total volume of labour units.
The term &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B_2&lt;/script&gt; I was first not sure how to interpret. Is it total consumption of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;, ie. is it equal to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_2&lt;/script&gt;? In this case the equality would not work out, since &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M_{21} = 1/9 = h_2 l_1 X_1 = h_2 \frac{1}{3} \frac{2}{3} = h_2 \frac{2}{9}&lt;/script&gt;, therefore &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h_2=1/2&lt;/script&gt; (by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M_{21}&lt;/script&gt; I mean 2nd row 1st column of matrix).
Therefore &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B_2 = 7/36&lt;/script&gt;, which is equal to total wages (or consumption from wages since we assume all wages are spent), ie. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B_2 = V_1 + V_2&lt;/script&gt;. Then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h_2 = B_2/L = \frac{V_1+V_2}{L}&lt;/script&gt; means the ratio of worker consumption to all labour performed, it is basically the labour share (again there is some issue here about money vs. physical units, but let us put that aside for the moment). There is also here the assumption that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h_2&lt;/script&gt;, the labour share is the same in both sectors.
The product &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l_1 h_2&lt;/script&gt; then means the share of living labour in the gross output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; times the &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; workers receive per unit of labour. In summary it is the amount of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; to be ‘inputted’ (wage paid to workers that will be spent on &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;) to the department for a unit of its output, this is how it plays the same role as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a_{ij}&lt;/script&gt; in input-output terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally to go from physical/labour units to prices there is a price for units of &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_2&lt;/script&gt;. I drop these from the rest of the derivation by setting them to 1. Then we can write the entire I/O matrix symbolically:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; (inputs)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; (inputs)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;dC (new C)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;dV (new V)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;u (capitalist consum.)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt; (total output)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; (outputs)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_1 a_{11} X_1 = p_1 X_{11}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_1 a_{12} X_2 = p_1 X_{12}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_1 dA&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_1 X_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; (outputs)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_2 h_2 l_1 X_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_2 h_2 l_2 X_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_2 dh&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_2 C_k&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_2 X_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;S_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W_i&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_1 X_1&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_2 X_2&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 4: I/O table of expanded reproduction in Leontief categories&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_2 h_2 l_2 X_2&lt;/script&gt; for instance means the amount of &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; to be used by the workers of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;, equal to &lt;em&gt;(unit price) x (labour share in net income) x (share of net income (living labour) in gross output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;) x (gross output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_1 a_{12} X_2&lt;/script&gt; is the money output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; required by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;, and it is the &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; used up by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;, equal to &lt;em&gt;(unit price) x (units of MoP used for one unit of gross output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;) x (gross output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full system for expanded reproduction can be captured for both departments (after cancelling out the price terms), with inputs equaling outputs, as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;a_{11}X_1 + a_{12} X_2 + da = X_1
\tag{3}\label{eq3}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;h_2 l_1 X_1 + h_2 l_2 X_2 + dh + C_k = X_2
\tag{4}\label{eq4}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or in matrix notation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{bmatrix} X_1\\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} a_{11} &amp; a_{12}\\ 0 &amp; 0\\ \end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix} X_1\\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix} + \begin{bmatrix} 0\\ h_2\\ \end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix} l_1 &amp; l_2 \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} X_1\\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix}
+ \begin{bmatrix} da\\ dh + C_k \end{bmatrix}
\tag{5}\label{eq5} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vector on the right represents ‘final demand’ (or final output), these parts of the output can be used to expand the labour force and the capital stock, or spent on consumption by the owners who receive the profits. Final demand does not include consumption of workers from wages, as this is to reproduce the existing labour force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using column vectors one can write Equation \eqref{eq5} as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\mathbf{X} = \mathbf{A X} + \mathbf{h} [\mathbf{l X}] + \mathbf{F}
\tag{6}\label{eq6}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;with &lt;strong&gt;F&lt;/strong&gt; representing the column vector of final demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to recover the multiplier relationship of Equation 9 of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mbkoltai.github.io/reprod_multipl&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. To do that, the ‘&lt;em&gt;net output&lt;/em&gt;’ is first defined as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q = (I - A)X&lt;/script&gt;, with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;I&lt;/script&gt; the identity matrix. Writing it explicitly this is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
Q = (I - A) X = \begin{bmatrix} 1 - a_{11} &amp; - a_{12}\\ 0 &amp; 1\\ \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} X_1\\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix} = \\ =
\begin{bmatrix} X_1 - a_{11}X_1 - a_{12} X_2 \\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix}
= \mathbf{h} [\mathbf{l X}] + \mathbf{F}
\tag{7}\label{eq7} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So ‘&lt;em&gt;net output&lt;/em&gt;’ means for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; its gross output minus the part that is to replace the constant capital used up in this period of production, and for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt; its entire output.
&lt;!--- If we say *MoP* produced in the current period is also used up in this period (its part directed to replacement, $$I-A$$), whereas all *CoG* is used up after production, then it is maybe more intuitive why the net product is defined as $$\mathbf{h} [\mathbf{l X}] + \mathbf{F}$$.--&gt;
There is a temporal order of events here, ie. movements of money (eg. when wages are paid out and then spent etc.) and movements and use of physical goods that is not trivial and I want to reconstruct later on in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First though I will follow through with the derivation of Chapter 2. Using Equation \eqref{eq7} and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} = l (I-A)^{-1}&lt;/script&gt;, Equation \eqref{eq6} can be re-expressed as:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q \frac{v}{l} = A Q \frac{v}{l} + h [l Q \frac{v}{l}] + F = A Q \frac{v}{l} + h [v Q ] + F&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subtracting &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A Q \frac{v}{l}&lt;/script&gt;, the left-side simplifies to  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{v}{l}Q (I-A) = (I-A)^{-1} (I-A) Q = Q&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Q = h [v Q ] + F
\tag{8}\label{eq8}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a relationship between:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the net product &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q&lt;/script&gt; as defined in Eq. \eqref{eq7}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{h}&lt;/script&gt; that is the column vector &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\begin{bmatrix}  0 \\  h_2 \\ \end{bmatrix}&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h_2 = B_2/L = \frac{V_1+V_2}{L}&lt;/script&gt;, the ratio of worker consumption to all labour performed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v}&lt;/script&gt;, which is the row vector of ‘vertically integrated labour coefficients’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v}&lt;/script&gt;, let us do the multiplication:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\mathbf{v} = l (I - A)^{-1} =
\begin{bmatrix} l_1 &amp; l_2 \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} \frac{1}{1 - a_{11}} &amp; \frac{a_{12}}{1-a_{11}} \\ 0 &amp; 1\\ \end{bmatrix} =
\begin{bmatrix} \frac{l_1}{1 - a_{11}} &amp; l_1 \frac{a_{12}}{1-a_{11}} + l_2 \end{bmatrix}
\tag{9}\label{eq9} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not very intuitive, but if we realize that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a_{11}X_1 = X_{11} = C_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a_{12}X_2 = X_{12} = C_2&lt;/script&gt; (since &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C_2&lt;/script&gt; are the amounts of constant capital transferred into the output, while &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_{11}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_{12}&lt;/script&gt; are parts of the output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_1&lt;/script&gt; that go into replacement) and that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_i = L_i + C_i&lt;/script&gt;, then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v}&lt;/script&gt; simplifies to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\mathbf{v} = \begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 1 \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;. This is partly because I previously dropped unit prices &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_1&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p_2&lt;/script&gt; (by setting them to 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing, let us note that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} Q&lt;/script&gt; is a scalar, since &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v}&lt;/script&gt; is a 2-column row vector and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q&lt;/script&gt; a 2-row column vector. Therefore if we multiply both sides of Equation \eqref{eq8} by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v}&lt;/script&gt;, we get&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v}Q = \mathbf{v} h [v Q ] + \mathbf{v} F
\tag{10}\label{eq10}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving the first term on the LHS and factoring out &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v}Q&lt;/script&gt;, we finally arrive at&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\boxed{ \mathbf{v}Q = \frac{1}{1 - \mathbf{v} h} \mathbf{v} F }
\tag{11}\label{eqmult}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which is again a multiplier relationship, very similar to Equation 9 in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mbkoltai.github.io/reprod_multipl&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; where only net income was considered, but now constant capital has also been accounted for. It is a relationship between final demand &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} F&lt;/script&gt; and the net income (all new value added = wages + profits) &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;vQ&lt;/script&gt;.
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} h&lt;/script&gt; is a scalar, as is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} F&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} Q&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;vQ&lt;/script&gt; is net income (= total employment of labour units = total new value added) because &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} = l (I - A)^{-1}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Q = (I - A)X&lt;/script&gt; (net product = to-be-accumulated capital &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dA&lt;/script&gt; + all output of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_2&lt;/script&gt;, ie &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;X_2&lt;/script&gt; ). Therefore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\mathbf{v}Q = \mathbf{l} \mathbf{X} = \begin{bmatrix} L_1/X_1 &amp; L_2/X_2 \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} X_1 \\ X_2 \end{bmatrix} = L_1 + L_2
\tag{12}\label{eq12} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so the meaning of this term is quite clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} h&lt;/script&gt; in the denominator, it is the &lt;em&gt;propensity to consume&lt;/em&gt;. As discussed above &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt; is the labour share (wages to net income/total labour) or in other words workers’ consumption divided by total labour performed (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h_2 = B_2/L&lt;/script&gt;).
In the ‘net income’ (‘Keynesian’) analysis of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbkoltai.github.io/reprod_multipl/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; (see Equation 1 and 9) &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;b&lt;/script&gt; was &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; consumption, whereas here &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B_2&lt;/script&gt; is only consumption from wages, so the multiplier formulas are not identical. Since &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} = [1 \ 1]&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{h} = \begin{bmatrix} 0 \\ h_2 \end{bmatrix}&lt;/script&gt;, then the product is
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} h = h_2 = B_2 / L&lt;/script&gt;
or wages paid out (and spent on consumption) per unit of labour performed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the product &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v F&lt;/script&gt; is the value of the products corresponding to final demand, and if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v = [1 \ 1]&lt;/script&gt;, then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} \mathbf{F} = F_1 + F_2 = dA + dH + C_k&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, Equation \eqref{eqmult} expresses the relationship between net income, workers’ consumption (per unit of labour performed) and final demand (the surplus product). The multiplier relationship can be derived in the two-department model of the reproduction schema, that considers constant capital as well. A difference is that the ratio of net income to final demand here is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1/(1- vh)&lt;/script&gt; where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v h}&lt;/script&gt; is &lt;em&gt;workers’&lt;/em&gt; consumption per unit of labour, and not total consumption &lt;a href=&quot;https://mbkoltai.github.io/reprod_multipl/&quot;&gt;as previously&lt;/a&gt;. (Or: labour embodied (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v}&lt;/script&gt;) in the bundle consumed by workers per unit of labour (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{h}&lt;/script&gt;).) Then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e = 1 - \mathbf{v h}&lt;/script&gt; is the share of surplus value extracted from each unit of labour. If we say that for simplicity &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v} = \mathbf{p}&lt;/script&gt; (prices and values are the same), so that net money output is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y = \mathbf{v Q} = \mathbf{p Q}&lt;/script&gt; and money final demand &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f = \mathbf{vF} = \mathbf{pF}&lt;/script&gt;, then Equation \eqref{eqmult} can be expressed as a ‘macro income multiplier’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;y = \frac{1}{e}f
\tag{13}\label{eq13}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the concept of surplus value (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e&lt;/script&gt;) and the multiplier relationship between final demand (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f&lt;/script&gt;) and net money output (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y&lt;/script&gt;) can be related in a 2-sector model taking into account constant capital. Or, if you like, the concepts of classical political economy (such as surplus value) and those of ‘Keynesian economics’ can be related through the reproduction schemas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me this relationship seems an algebraic one between parts of the total output classified with respect to their use: the net output on the one hand and on the other ‘final demand’ (or final output), which is the part that can be consumed by owners or take the form of &lt;em&gt;MoP&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;CoG&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;expand&lt;/em&gt; the capital stock (over replacement) and the workforce. The second chunk (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{F}&lt;/script&gt; in the above notation), that is the surplus part of the output, is a part of the first (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v Q}&lt;/script&gt;). In other words, final demand is the part of the net output that can be directed to accumulation (=new workers + new constant capital) or consumption from profit.
This is not a causal relationship in my understanding, but an algebraic identity. In fact, these purchases from profit for consumption and accumulation occur at the end of a period of production, and first - it seems to me - what we should explain is where the demand for these parts of the total output comes from. It is this question that I want to address in my next post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/title/marxian-reproduction-schema-money-and-aggregate-demand-in-a-capitalist-economy/oclc/946076663&quot;&gt;Andrew Trigg, Marxian reproduction schema: money and aggregate demand in a capitalist economy. Routledge, 2009&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="political-economy" /><category term="economic-models" /><category term="classical-political-economy" /><category term="marxian-economics" /><summary type="html">Reproduction and input-output analysis</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Embedding equations in GitHub blog posts with MathJax</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/embed-equations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embedding equations in GitHub blog posts with MathJax" /><published>2018-09-25T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/embed-equations</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/embed-equations/">&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I wanted to do for this blog was to be able to write equations as in LaTeX. I thought this would be straightforward, but it took some searching to find a better solution than embedding images of the equations generated by an external tool.
The simple answer is: use MathJax that has a syntax almost identical to LaTeX. More recent GitHub themes (I forked &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/barryclark/jekyll-now&quot;&gt;Jekyll Now&lt;/a&gt;) already have kramdown enabled in the &lt;em&gt;_config.yml&lt;/em&gt; file, supporting MathJax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steps are then the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) If you want to use equations in your blog posts as I do, paste the following script into &lt;em&gt;post.html&lt;/em&gt; that should be in your &lt;em&gt;layouts&lt;/em&gt; folder&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
        MathJax.Hub.Config({
            config: [&quot;MMLorHTML.js&quot;],
            extensions: [&quot;tex2jax.js&quot;,&quot;TeX/AMSmath.js&quot;,&quot;TeX/AMSsymbols.js&quot;],
            jax: [&quot;input/TeX&quot;],
            tex2jax: {
                inlineMath: [ ['$','$'], [&quot;\\(&quot;,&quot;\\)&quot;] ],
                displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'], [&quot;\\[&quot;,&quot;\\]&quot;] ],
                processEscapes: false
            },
            TeX: {
                TagSide: &quot;right&quot;,
                TagIndent: &quot;.8em&quot;,
                MultLineWidth: &quot;85%&quot;,
                equationNumbers: {
                   autoNumber: &quot;AMS&quot;,
                },
                unicode: {
                   fonts: &quot;STIXGeneral,'Arial Unicode MS'&quot;
                }
            },
            showProcessingMessages: false
        });
&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;within the block&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{ % if page.mathjax % }&lt;br /&gt;
(code comes here)&lt;br /&gt;
{ % endif % }&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that you can set up a &lt;em&gt;mathjax&lt;/em&gt; flag for those posts where you’ll have equations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) In the posts where you’ll have equations insert the flag&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;mathjax: true&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) You can now write equations between double $ signs. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;\begin{bmatrix} X_1\\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} a_{11} &amp;amp; a_{12}\\ 0 &amp;amp; 0\\ \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} X_1\\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix}
+ \begin{bmatrix} 0\\ h_2\\ \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} l_1 &amp;amp; l_2 \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} X_1\\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix}
+ \begin{bmatrix} da\\ dh + C_k \end{bmatrix}  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;becomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{bmatrix} X_1\\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} a_{11} &amp; a_{12}\\ 0 &amp; 0\\ \end{bmatrix}
    \begin{bmatrix} X_1\\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix} + \begin{bmatrix} 0\\ h_2\\ \end{bmatrix}
    \begin{bmatrix} l_1 &amp; l_2 \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} X_1\\ X_2\\ \end{bmatrix}
    + \begin{bmatrix} da\\ dh + C_k \end{bmatrix} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good resource for different formulae &lt;a href=&quot;https://math.meta.stackexchange.com/questions/5020/mathjax-basic-tutorial-and-quick-reference&quot;&gt;is here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tools" /><category term="github-blog" /><summary type="html">Steps to enable inserting equations</summary></entry></feed>